<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvay unto true Christian unitie the worship of God in spirit and in truth : together vvith many spirituall benefits therein received now in this life and everlastingly ...</title>
            <author>Reeve, Edmund, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2196</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12576885</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12576885</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63618</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58331)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63618)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 331:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvay unto true Christian unitie the worship of God in spirit and in truth : together vvith many spirituall benefits therein received now in this life and everlastingly ...</title>
                  <author>Reeve, Edmund, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Legatt and are to be sold by Edward Wright ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edmund Reeve. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Concord --  Religious aspects.</term>
               <term>Christian union.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63618:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VVAY <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTO TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E</hi> Chriſtian Unitie: <hi>The worſhip of God in Spirit and in Truth:</hi> TOGETHER VVith many Spirituall benefits therein received now in this life, and everlaſtingly. All expreſly delivered in the Holy Scripture, And declared in an Expoſition of a certain Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall portion of the Sacred Text. Written for the leſſening of Differences, and for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of Concord in the godly truth eternall. Alſo for to make more manifeſt a firme Ground, whereon holy Unity may be built up, unto the higheſt degree of perfection, attainable in this World.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Behold, how good and how pleaſant it is, for brethren to dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 133.1.</hi>
               </bibl> 
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But the houre commeth, and now is, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth: for the Father ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſuch to worſhip Him. </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh.
4.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Illo tempore nihil tam conveniens ſervo Dei videbatur, quàm Unitatem ſequi.</p>
               <bibl>Hieron. cont. Lucif. cap. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Legatt,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Edward Wright,</hi> at the ſigne of the Bible neere <hi>Pie-corner,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63618:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63618:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To my very loving and much honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red friend and neighbour, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. JOHN BATHURST Doctour of Phyſick in <hi>London,</hi> be the gracious accompliſhment of the promiſe, which Godlineſſe hath, of the life that now is,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> and of that which is to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He eternall God (bleſſed for ever) ſaying:<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 8.22.</note>
               <hi>Is there no Balme in Gilead? Is there no Phyſician there? Why then is not the health of the daughter of my people recovered?</hi> ſignifieth thereby, that as there is ſalve for corporall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie; ſo is there likewiſe for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall maladie. And therefore He that
<hi>hath</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>healing in His wings,</hi> having pronounced,<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 9.12.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The ſick have need of a Phyſician;</hi> hath taught there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, That<note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 55.2,
3.</note> endeavour ſhould be for health in ſoule, <hi>Ut ſit mens</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſana in corpore ſano.</hi> Alſo like as the Sentence ſaith concerning what is bodily,<note n="f" place="margin">Sir. 38.4.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>The Lord hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted medicines out of the earth, and he that is wiſe will not abhorre them;</hi> ſo hath Hee out of his infinite wiſdome brought forth his moſt holy word; and whatſoever
<pb facs="tcp:63618:3"/> his Servants publiſh for to further ſpirituall welfare, and being the<note n="g" place="margin">Prov. 1.8.</note> true doctrine of the ſacred Scripture, it ſhould not be<note n="h" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.20, 21.</note> deſpiſed, but<note n="i" place="margin">Acts.
17.11.</note> taken into due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. It is a Saying among the Jewes,
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q> 
               <hi>A man learneth not ſo much of his own ſelf, as he learneth of another.</hi> One<note n="k" place="margin">Buxtorfius Lexico Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daico Rabbini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co ad radicem
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> expreſſeth it, <hi>Non tantum valet ſtudium privatum, quam id quod cum alio quis habet commune.</hi> The Almighty Creatour doth ſo<note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.8, 9, 10, 11, 25.</note> powre out of his Spirit upon the Myſticall body of his Sonne (to Whom be honour and glory everlaſtingly) as that one member may make uſe of another, according to his holy ordinance. Moreover, whereas the wiſe mans Exhortation is,<note n="m" place="margin">Sir. 38.1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Honour the Phyſician;</hi> and having my ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with you my much beloved neighbour and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician for bodily infirmities, and by Gods bleſſing find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much helpe and comfort from you; in mutuall love and thankefulneſſe I offer unto you theſe Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all counſels and ſoule-ſalves, praying that He, who is the true Tree of life, Whoſe <hi>leaves are for the</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rev. 22.2.</note> 
               <hi>healing of the Nations,</hi> may univerſally bleſſe them to you, yours, and all the<note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> Iſrael of God. And although ſome have (as the Apoſtle relateth)<note n="p" place="margin">Acts. 28.27.</note> refuſed to be healed; yet the Heavenly<note n="q" place="margin">Ezek. 2.7.</note> command was, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſpeake my words unto them, whether they will heare, or whether they will forbeare.</hi> Alſo howſoever unto them, which<note n="r" place="margin">Phil. 3.19. Luke. 12.20, 21. 2 Tim.
3.4.</note> minde and eſteeme moſt the earthly things, the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating and obſerving of ſuch matters, as are in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe following declared by the Word of the Lord to bee Chriſtian duties, may ſeeme<note n="ſ" place="margin">Job. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14, 15 Mal. 3.14.</note> unneceſſary; yet unto thoſe that will ſearch all the places of Scripture quoted therein, to know more and more the<note n="t" place="margin">Eph.
5 17. Rom. 12.2.</note> will of God for to doe<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 6.10. Pſ.
40.8.</note> it, there will<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 7.17. and 8.31, 32.</note> appeare, that the very true<note n="x" place="margin">2 Tim. 3, 5.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:63618:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Power of Godlineſſe is herein ſome manner teſtified. And whereas the myſteries of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt are more and more manifeſted, (praiſe be given to <hi>the high and loftie</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 57.15.</note> 
               <hi>One which inhabiteth eternity, whoſe Name is holy</hi>) there is hope that the greateſt meaſure of<note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 30.26. Rom. 11.12, 15, 26.</note> light therein, foretold in the Writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles to be given by God in the laſt Time, ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be enjoyed;<note n="*" place="margin">Nazianzenus oratione in lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Cypriani habita.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Divine Wiſdome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, long afore to lay the foundations of great matters, and to procure contraries through the contraries, that It be alſo had in the more admiration.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my lodging in the</hi> Old-Baily.</dateline>
               <signed>Yours ever reſpectively, E. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63618:4"/>
            <head>To the unpartiall Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is one of the <hi>Arabian</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 8.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> In libro cui titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Proverbio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Arabico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum centuriae duae.</note> proverbs: Looke not unto him that ſpeaketh; but unto what he ſpeakes. And the Holy Ghoſt ſaith: The wiſdome which is from above, is without<note n="b" place="margin">Jam. 3.17.</note> partiality.<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 53.6.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> writeth, That we all like ſheep have gone aſtray; we have turned every one to his owne way. Now it is the will and commandement of God, (as<note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 50.6.</note> 
               <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> ſignifieth) That wee ſhould not paſſe our time in this world, going from mountaine to hill, and forgetting our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting place; but (as it is taught in <hi>Ezechiel</hi>) our<note n="e" place="margin">Ezech. 34.14,
15.</note> Fold ſhould be upon the high Mountaines of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> there to feed in a good paſture: alſo to<note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 33.12. Zeph. 3.12, 13.</note> lie downe, as ſaith the <hi>Lord.</hi> There have been ſome in theſe latter times, which by their writings endeavoured to promote Unitie, becauſe they ſaw it teſtified, That the multitude of them which beleeved, were of<note n="g" place="margin">Acts. 4.32.</note> one heart, and of one ſoule. Alſo that the Apoſtle ſaid:<note n="h" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.18.</note> walked we not in the ſame ſpirit? walked we not in the ſame ſteps? Yea <hi>Chriſt</hi> foretold, That there ſhall be<note n="i" place="margin">Joh. 10.16. See Mat. 9.36, 37, 38. 1 Cor. 1.10, 11, 12,
13.</note> one fold, and one ſhepheard. And therefore ſo fervently prayed for his people, That they all may be<note n="k" place="margin">Joh. 17.11, 21, 21, 23. See 1. Cor. 12.12, 13. and 3.3,
4.</note> one; as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us: That they may be one even as we are one; I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore now duly conſider, what <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in his time delivered furthering unto godly Unitie; the which doctrine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:63618:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> each of the<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 3.2, 3. Mar. 1.1, 2, 3. Luk. 3.3, 4,
5, 6. Joh. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> in ſome manner rehearſed, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for that time. And if wee throughly weigh the ſaid Oracle, we ſhall finde it<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> requiſite to be conſidered by every one at this preſent. Moreover the Reader is to be admoniſhed, that he do not<note n="n" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.12. 2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> condemne, what he underſtandeth not in this enſuing Treatiſe, remembring that <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith:<note n="o" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16, 17. See verſe 9. Eph. 3.4. Col. 1.27. and 2.2. 1 Cor. 12.3. 1 Pet. 2.2.</note> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controverſie great is the myſterie of Godlineſſe. Alſo afore any one can well judge concerning the moſt high Myſteries of the Goſpel, he is firſt rightly to underſtand the<note n="p" place="margin">Heb.
5.12, 13, 14. and 6.1, 2.</note> principles of the doctrine of Chriſt, as the Apoſtle ſignifieth unto the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes.</hi> Who alſo gave the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for to know, that ſuch as are but babes or little Children in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Cannot<note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.2. Joh. 16.12.</note> beare the ſtrong meat of the word. And if ſuch of the firſt age in Chriſt, cannot<note n="r" place="margin">Gal. 4.1.2. Acts. 1.6, 7. 1 Cor.
2.6.</note> comprehend all things belonging to the great myſterie of Chriſtianity; then how can thoſe, which are not<note n="ſ" place="margin">Joh. 3.3. See Rom. 12.1, 2.</note> changed in mind and converſation, according as the Goſpel preſcribeth, (or are not unfeinedly ſtriving to attain the ſaid change) judge rightly concerning the moſt high ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all matters, ſeeing that it is written:<note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> The naturall man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth not the things of the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> for they are foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe unto him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned. The holy Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith:<note n="u" place="margin">Dan. 12.10.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall be purified and made white, and tried: but the wicked ſhall do wickedly: and none of the wicked ſhall underſtand.<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 25.14.9.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> ſaith: The Secret of the <hi>Lord</hi> is with them that fear him; and He will ſhew them His covenant. The meek will He guide in judgement, and the meek will he teach His way. It is written, that the Diſciples came unto
<hi>Chriſt;</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 13.10, 11. Iſa. 8.16.</note> Why ſpeakeſt thou unto the Multitude in parables? He anſwered and ſaid unto them, Becauſe it is given unto you to know the myſteries of the Kingdome of heaven, but unto them it is not given. Who alſo ſaid unto His <hi>Father:</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 11.25.26, 27. See Joh. 8.31, 32. Wiſd. 1.4. and 6.23. Sirach 3.19, 20. and 43.33. and 51.20. Dan. 9 13. Pſ. 19.7, 8. and 119.98,
99, 100. Iſa. 60.1, 2. Joh. 14 17.</note> Thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto babes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:63618:5"/>Now theſe Scriptures are mentioned, that the Reader may duly conſider, That no perſon how learned ſoever in Humane Literature, or in the hiſtory of Sacred Writ, which is not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the true Regeneration, can<note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 28.5. Mat. 19.28.</note> rightly judge concerning the high things pertaining unto <hi>God.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith<note n="z" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.29. and 4.7, 8. Joh. 3.3, 5, 6.</note> Knowing this firſt, that no propheſie of the Scripture is of any private interpretation: for the propheſie came not in<note n="*" place="margin">See the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall reading.</note> any time by the will of man: but holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt. And therefore the Apoſtle
<hi>Paul</hi> ſaith:<note n="b" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.20, 21.</note> No man can ſay, (namly with true underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Lord,</hi> but by the holy Ghoſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us unfeinedly endeavour to become truly<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.15,
12.</note> ſpirituall, and then (as the Apoſtle ſignifieth) wee ſhall bee able more and more to judge (or,<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.3.</note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">As it is in the margent.</note> diſcerne) all things, which<note n="e" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.3.</note> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto life and godlines. The holy and righteous Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Spirit, that filleth both heaven and<note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 23.24.</note> earth,<note n="g" place="margin">Joh. 16.13.</note> guide us into all His truth eternall, that we may receive and enjoy all <note n="h" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8. Eph. 3.20, 21.</note> comfort, which He vouchſafeth unto his Servants, now and everlaſtingly, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Edmund Reeve</hi> Bachelour in Divinity, and Inſtructer in all the Tongues pertaining thereunto.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63618:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A way unto true Chriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 40.3, 4, 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q> 
                  <note place="margin">See concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Text, what is delivered after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in this Treatiſe, and in the margin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto it.</note>A voice crying: In the Wilderneſſe prepare ye the way of the <hi>Lord,</hi> make ſtraight in the Deſart an high way for our <hi>God.</hi> Let every valley be filled up, let everie Mountain and hill be caſt down, and what is crooked let it be made ſtraight, and the roughneſſes become ſmoothneſſe: and the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall be revealed, and all Fleſh ſhall ſee it together; for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T being written in the beginning of this Chapter,<note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 40.1,
2.</note> Comfort ye, comfort yee my people, ſaith your <hi>God.</hi> Speake yee comfortably to
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and cry unto her, That her<note n="*" place="margin">So is the Tranſlation in the margent.</note> appointed time is accompliſhed, that her iniquitie is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned: for ſhe hath received of the <hi>Lords</hi> hand double for all her ſinnes. Then the ſaid heavenlie voice is uttered, to be conſidered moſt ſeriouſly, viz. In the Wilderneſſe prepare ye the way of the Lord,<note place="margin">The former part of the cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voice is a kinde of figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſpeaking.</note> &amp;c. The which crying voice from heaven unto us, is in the former part thereof a kinde of Figurative ſpeaking, ſignifying, That as if the greateſt
<hi>Emperour</hi> were to goe into a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe or deſart, for to make his abode there, he would <note n="*" place="margin">As is expreſſed in Iſa. 40.3, 4.</note> expect ſuch like preparation for his comming: So <hi>Chriſt</hi> in His ſpirituall comming to make his<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 14.23: Mal. 3.1. Pſa. 101.2.</note> abode
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63618:6"/> within His people, doth expect the like<note n="c" place="margin">Amos. 4.12. Iſa. 64.4, 5. The ſaid crying voice is a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Scripture of moſt ſpeciall conſideration.</note> preparing to be made ſpiritually. Now this whole portion of Scripture, is as it were a ſumme even of all the generall doctrine of the word of <hi>God.</hi> And therefore it is moſt diligently to be noted. Yea it is a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>See Luke 11.52.</p>
                  <p>In Marke. 1.1, 2. The ſaid duty of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to be the doctrine of the beginning of the Goſpel of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And therfore it is moſt ſeriouſly to bee minded. The late learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Caſaubon ſaid: Myſterium in hac hiſtoria à pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta Eſaia. olim praedicta, et tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtudio à ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis Evangeliſtis adnotata, latere aliquid majus ſuſpicor, quam aut capere ipſe ſatis, aut ſatis queam admirari. In annal. Baron exers.</hi> 136.</p>
                  <p>The Title of the ſaid portion of Scripture.</p>
               </note> key of true holie knowledge: for who ſo doth rightly apprehend the minde of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in this Oracle, he ſhall thereby through Divine help be enabled much to perceive of the myſterie, which is throughout the whole word of <hi>God.</hi> And that it may be the eaſier comprehended, let meditation be thereon in this order. Firſt, to conſider, for whom preparation is here preſcribed to be made. Secondly, in what place it is to be. Thirdly, the mentioned particular works of the ſaid preparation. And fourthly, the benefit which now commeth in a true endeavour to perform the ſame.</p>
            <p>But afore entrance be into the explanation of theſe points, it is meet in briefe to note the Title of this Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Sacred Text. And literally according to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> it is, A voice crying, or, a crying voice, or, a voice of a Crier, the<note n="*" place="margin">The Hebrew accent over the word for <hi>Crier,</hi> maketh a <hi>comma:</hi> but the accent over the word for
<hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is ſaid to be one of thoſe which make an halfe <hi>Comma.</hi>
               </note> point of Diſtinction being made at the word crying. For ſo it ought to be by vertue of the
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> accent unto the ſaid word in the Originall;<note n="*" place="margin">It is alſo ſo pointed or diſſinguiſhed in their Tranſlation, Printed <hi>anno</hi> 1624. Mr.
<hi>Tindall</hi> in his Tranſlation hath there made the diſtinction alſo. See the Tranſlation uſed in the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt.</note> as in the annotation on this place it is delivered, which is unto the tranſlation ſet forth by <hi>Tremellius</hi> and <hi>Junius.</hi> Now this moſt great matter thus from <hi>Almighty God</hi> delivered by
<hi>Iſaiah,</hi> is called a voice crying, to wit, unto us in the name of the <hi>Lord,</hi> for to ſignifie that every<note n="d" place="margin">Mar. 6.12. 2 Tim. 4.2.</note> true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> is a teacher of this Doctrine in effect, and fervently preſſeth the ſame. Alſo, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63618:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> preached it, ſo did <hi>John</hi> the<note n="e" place="margin">Luk 3.3,
4, 5, 6.</note> Baptiſt. Yea<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> and His
<note n="g" place="margin">Acts 20.21.</note> Apoſtles did in ſubſtance publiſh the ſame. It appeareth to be ſaid <hi>Crying,</hi> becauſe the world is fallen into a great
<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 56.10. Mat. 25.5. Luke 17.34. 1 Theſ. 5.6.7.</note> ſleep of ignorance: yea innumerable lie<note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 2.1. 1 Pet. 4.6.</note> dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſinnes. Whereupon <hi>God</hi> commandeth every of his Miniſters, ſaying:<note n="k" place="margin">Jſa. 58.1.</note> Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy voice like a Trumpet, &amp;c. Alſo there is ſaid:<note n="l" place="margin">Eph. 5.14.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall give thee light.<note place="margin">The firſt point<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for whom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is to be made.</note> Let us now conſider the firſt point, namely, for whom preparation is here preſcribed to be made. The Text ſaith, For the <hi>Lord,</hi> For our <hi>God.</hi> And the name here rendred<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> See <hi>Shi nale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and <hi>Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torfias</hi> in their
<hi>Lexicons.</hi> at <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lord</hi> is obſerved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in it the ſignification <hi>Was, Is, Will be.</hi> And ſo <hi>in Rev.</hi> 1.8. and 4.8. even ſuch an expreſſion is delivered. And the name rendred<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ex
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, et <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>God,</hi> is noted to ſignifie a
<hi>Mightie Being:</hi> and is here conſidered alſo to have in it the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the bleſſed<note n="*" place="margin">Being, in the Text in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall number.</note>
               <hi>Trinitie.</hi> And the word <hi>our</hi> being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereunto, declareth Him to be the
<hi>God,</hi> whom the holie Prophet enjoyed. And ſaith <hi>David.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 144.15. and 33 12.</note> Happy is that people, whoſe <hi>God</hi> is the
<hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that this <hi>Lord God</hi> may be continually with us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to His gracious<note n="p" place="margin">Exod. 33.13, 14, 15.</note> preſence, this Oracle inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth us, what we for our parts are to do thereunto. But foraſmuch<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 1.3. Ezek. 8.12. Pſ.
73.27, 28.</note> few doe underſtand, that the ſaid preſence may be enjoyed now, whileſt we are in the body, in this life, and in this preſent world: it is neceſſarie to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for to help mans weak apprehenſion herein.<note place="margin">
                  <p>God is every where, though moſt mind it not. There is no place, where Hee is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his <hi>Eſſence</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Spirit.</hi> Wee are to believe, that thus <hi>God</hi> is. Heb. 11.6. Acts 17.27. Pſ. 139.</p>
                  <p>Nos verò omnibus [non modo factu ſed etiam] cogitationibus et ſermonibus noſtris, tum nocta n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n interdiu Deum adeſſe ſcimus: Eumque et totum eſſe lumen, et quae in cordibus noſtris latent videre. Athenagoras in legatione pro Chriſtianis.</p>
               </note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let there be firſt conſidered, that the eternall <hi>God</hi> (bleſſed for ever) according to His Eſſence, infinite ſpirit, or immenſe Being, is perpetually every where in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall world. It is an ancient ſaying:
<hi>Enter, praefemer, Deus
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63618:7"/> heic, &amp; ubique, potenter.</hi> He ſaith:<note n="r" place="margin">Iſa.
66.1.</note> Heaven is my throne, and the earth is my foot-ſtoole. And, can any<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ier. 23.24. See Acts. 7.49, 50. 2. Chro. 6.18. Iſa. 43.2.</note> hide himſelf in ſecret places, that I ſhall not ſee him, ſaith the <hi>Lord?</hi> Doe not I fill heaven and earth, ſaith the <hi>Lord?</hi> There is alſo written:<note n="t" place="margin">Wiſd.
1.7.</note> The Spirit of the <hi>Lord</hi> filleth the world: and that which containeth all things hath know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the voice.<note n="u" place="margin">Wiſd. 12.1.</note> Thine incorruptible ſpirit is in all things.</p>
            <p>Moreover according to the aforeſaid manner he is continually within every one of us, although<note n="*" place="margin">Job. 9.11. Joh. 1.5.</note> undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by us. This incomprehenſible <hi>God</hi> was unknown to the<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acts. 17.23, 27, 28.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prope Deus eſt, tecum eſt, intus eſt. Ita dico. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cili, ſacer intra nos ſpiritus ſedet, bonorum malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noſtrorum obſervator, et cuſtos. Hic prout à nobis tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; ita et nos tractat ipſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca ad Lucili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Athenians;</hi> and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> preached Him unto them, and ſignified, That they ſhould ſeeke the
<hi>Lord,</hi> if haply they might feele after him and find him, though he be not farre from every one of us. For in him wee live, and move, and have our being. And <hi>David</hi> hath written almoſt a whole<note n="y" place="margin">Pſa. 139.</note> Pſalm, for to teach, that the Spirit of <hi>God (Gods</hi> preſence) was continually with him, and that he could go no whither, where the <hi>Lord</hi> was not. And in concluſion he ſaid:<note n="z" place="margin">verſe
18.</note> When I awake, I am ſtill with thee. When one duly conſidereth, what hath operation within him, and becomes ſenſible, that in him ſomewhat<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 1.29. Prov. 1.23. Acts 7.51.</note> mooveth him towards the obſerving of the ten Commandements, and what elſe is that everlaſting Law of Almighty <hi>God,</hi> he then thus awaked, ſaith with
<hi>David:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 73.23.</note> I am ſtill with thee, <hi>O God;</hi> and thou art<note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 23.4.</note> with mee. It is written that <hi>Jacob</hi> being awaked out of his ſleep at a certaine time, ſaid: Surely, the <hi>Lord</hi> is in this<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <p>Gen. 28.16.</p>
                  <p>It is neceſſary to underſtand ſo farre forth as it is in Scripture expreſſed, what the eternall <hi>God</hi> is, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite <hi>Eſſence</hi> or being.</p>
               </note> place, and I knew it not. But that this firſt point may yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more cleare unto devout ſoules, namely, for whom preparation is now to be made, according to the doctrine of this heavenly crying voice, there is alſo to be ſignified in ſome wiſe, what the Scripture ſaith; That the eternall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63618:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>God</hi> is. And ſo the minde of man ſeeking the <hi>Lord,</hi> may be introducted to ſee (though as through a glaſſe) the<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa.
33.17.</note> 
               <hi>King</hi> in his beauty; and to behold the <hi>Land</hi> that is very farre off, as <hi>Jſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh. The <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid to the woman of
<hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Joh. 4.23, 24 See 2. Cor. 3.17, 18. and the marginall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>God</hi> is Spirit.</note> The houre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and now is, when the true worſhippers ſhall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>Father</hi> in Spirit and in truth: for the <hi>Father</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſuch to worſhip him, declareth, That <hi>God</hi> is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and that they which worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in truth. Where he teacheth us, that <hi>God</hi> is Spirit. <hi>S. John</hi> ſaith: This then is the meſſage which we have heard of him, and declare unto you, that <hi>God</hi> is<note n="g" place="margin">1. Joh. 1.5.
<hi>God</hi> is Light.</note> Light, and in him is no darkneſſe at all. He alſo ſaith: Beloved, let us love one another; for love is of <hi>God:</hi> and every one that loveth, is borne of <hi>God,</hi> and knoweth <hi>God.</hi> He that loveth not, knoweth not <hi>God;</hi> for
<hi>God</hi> is<note n="h" place="margin">1. John. 4.7, 8, 16. <hi>God</hi> is Love.</note> love.
<hi>God</hi> is love, and hee that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> in him. So that here is plainely expreſſed, what <hi>God</hi> is, namely, that he is
<hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that this moſt bleſſed <hi>Spirit</hi> of light and love, may have his gracious preſence in us, to his<note n="i" place="margin">Prov. 8.31.</note> delight, and our unexpreſſable<note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 10.13.</note> good, His ſaid crying voice is unto us, that we in our wilderneſſe and deſart do prepare a way, and make ſtraight a path for Him.</p>
            <p>Now the ſecond point is to be conſidered; to wit,<note place="margin">The ſecond point, In what place to prepare the way of the <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </note> in what place the preparation is to be made. The Text ſaith, In the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> in the <hi>deſart.</hi> And what a ſpirituall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe or deſart is, it may appear out of the Apoſtles words unto the
<hi>Epheſians,</hi> deſcribing what they were, before they became<note n="l" place="margin">See Rom. 1.5. and 16.26. Acts. 6.7:</note> obedient unto the <hi>Faith.</hi> He ſaith unto them,<note n="m" place="margin">Eph. 2.12.</note> that at that time yee were without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> being aliens from the common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63618:8"/> ſtrangers from the covenants of promiſe, having no hope, and without
<hi>God</hi> in the world. But he deſcribeth a worſe wilderneſſe, in that his exhortation, where he ſaith:<note n="n" place="margin">Eph. 4.17, 18, 19.</note> This I ſay therefore, and teſtifie in the <hi>Lord,</hi> that yee henceforth walk not as other Gentiles walk, in the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their mind, having the underſtanding darkened, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alienated from the life of
<hi>God,</hi> through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſſe of their heart: who being paſt feeling, have given themſelves over unto laſciviouſneſſe, to worke all uncleanneſſe with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Now it is to be conſidered, how man and woman are become ſuch wilderneſſes and deſarts, whereas in the beginning they were created glorious<note n="o" place="margin">See
<hi>Cantic.</hi> 8.13. and 5.1, and 6.2. and 4.12.</note> gardens for the <hi>Lord. Solomon</hi> ſaith:<note n="p" place="margin">Eccles 7.29.</note> Loe, this only have I found, that <hi>God</hi> made man upright: but they have ſought out many inventions. It is ſaid in <hi>Geneſis:</hi> When the woman ſaw, <note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> that the tree of knowledge of good and evill was good for food, and that it was pleaſant unto the eyes, and a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, ſhe took thereof and did eate, and gave alſo to her husband with her, and he did eate. Then became they to be<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 3.7. Rom. 3.23.</note> naked in ſoul, and came ſhort of the glorie of <hi>God:</hi> They from being afore <hi>Gods</hi> gardens and paradiſes, now became to be wilderneſſes and deſarts. And that every one of mankind growing up in this world, and faſt abiding in the fall, not truly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to enter into the change of minde and life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and required by the Goſpel, for to proceed duly in the ſame, is a<note n="ſ" place="margin">Jſa. 32.15, 16. Jer. 4.26. Gen. 6.5. Rom. 3.12, 13, 14,
15, 16, 17, 18.</note> wilderneſſe and a deſart, it needeth no confirmation with many Texts, being acknowledged and confeſſed even by all. The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word for wilderneſſe is obſerved to ſignifie a place remote from ſpeech or talk. And in a ſetled ſpirituall Wilderneſſe there is ſcarfe any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63618:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> gracious ſpeech heard. Yea <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith:<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 12.34.35.</note> How can ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evill ſpeak good things? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>The Wilderneſſe within man, which ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, is the heart: My ſonne, ſaith
<hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Prov. 23.26.</note> give me thine heart. It is ſaid concerning <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> That he did evill, becauſe hee prepared not his<note n="*" place="margin">2. Chron. 12.14.</note> heart to ſeek the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whereas the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth here uſe two words, wilderneſſe and deſart; and the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word for <hi>deſart,</hi> hath in it the ſignification of<note n="x." place="margin">In Pſ. 68.4. in the plurall number.</note> 
               <hi>heaven,</hi> may it not inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the ſuperiour facultie in man, the underſtanding or the minde? And then by wilderneſſe may alſo be meant the inferiour facultie in man, the will or the affections. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeaking concerning many in his time, ſaith: My people is fooliſh, they have not known me; they are ſottiſh children, and they have no underſtanding: they are wiſe to do evill, but to do good they have no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. I beheld the earth, and loe, it was without forme and void: and the<note n="y" place="margin">Ier. 4.22, 23.</note> heavens, and they had no light. In which place alſo the word heaven appeareth to ſignifie mans mind or underſtanding.</p>
            <p>The<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 4.12. Luke. 1.46, 47. Iſa. 26.9.</note> Scripture hath in ſundry places the expreſſion of ſoule and ſpirit to be in man. But ſaith the Apoſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.23.</note> The very
<hi>God</hi> of peace ſanctifie you wholly: and I pray <hi>God,</hi> your whole ſpirit, and ſoule, &amp; body, bee preſerved blameles unto the comming of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Preparation is to be made thereunto in the whole man: and as inwardly, ſo outwardly alſo. And to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> he ſaith,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor.
6.19.20. The <hi>Vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> Text there hath <hi>Glorificate &amp; portate Deum in corpore veſtro</hi>
               </note> what know ye not that your body is the Temple of the holy Ghoſt which is in you, which ye have of <hi>God,</hi> and ye are not your own? For ye are bought with a price: therefore glorifie <hi>God</hi> in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63618:9"/> your body, and in your ſpirit, which are <hi>Gods.</hi> Now the next point is to be conſidered,<note place="margin">The third point The manner of preparing the way of the Lord in us.</note> the manner of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. And it is firſt expreſſed in generall, as, Prepare yee the way, make ſtraight an high way. And then the works of the ſaid preparation are expreſſed in particular, as namely; to exalt (or, fill up) every valley, &amp;c. The
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> word rendred prepare ye, is obſerved for to import alſo, to<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Schindlers Lexicon.</note> remove impediments, to void away out of ſight uncleanneſſes, &amp;c. The <hi>Lord</hi> by <hi>Malachi</hi> ſaith:<note n="d" place="margin">Mal. 3.1.</note> Behold, I will ſend my Meſſenger, and he ſhall prepare the way before me: and the <hi>Lord</hi> whom yee ſeeke, ſhall ſuddenly come to his Temple. And the Apoſtle having ſaid unto the <hi>Corinthians:</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2. Cor.
6.16</note> Yee are the Temple of the living God, as <hi>God</hi> hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, &amp;c. addeth this counſell: Having therefore theſe promiſes (dearly beloved) let us<note n="f" place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1.</note> cleanſe our ſelves from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſſe in the fear of God. So that the preparation doth much conſiſt in<note n="g" place="margin">1. Joh. 3.2, 3. Heb. 12.14.</note> purification of minde and life. Alſo whereas it is ſaid withall, make ſtraight an high way: and in S. <hi>Johns Goſpel</hi> the whole work of preparation is but thus expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note n="h" place="margin">Joh. 1.23.</note> Make ſtraight the way of the <hi>Lord,</hi> as ſaid the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſaias;</hi> the <hi>Arabicke</hi> interpretation of the ſaid verbe there, is not unworthy of ſome obſervation. It ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Make the way of the <hi>Lord</hi> eaſie. The ſaid <hi>Arabian</hi> verb is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted alſo, to make plain and convenient. So that for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſpirituall comming into us for to dwell in us, to walk within us,<note place="margin">See the <hi>Lexicon</hi> of
<hi>Raphelengius</hi>
               </note> to ſolace himſelf in us, and to worke all his works of grace within us, we are admoniſhed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, that his entrance and paſſage may be all manner of wayes delightſome unto him.<note place="margin">An expreſſing of the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, namely in 4. ſundry great workes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It followeth, that the particular works of the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be conſidered: and they are expreſſed in foure great
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63618:9"/> duties. But firſt, it is to be noted, That in an ancient<note n="I" place="margin">
                  <p>That which was in uſe in the Reigne of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt.</p>
                  <p>See <hi>Tindals</hi> Tranſlation.</p>
                  <p>See the note of <hi>Lucas Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> on this Text.</p>
                  <p>See Iſa. 57.14. Luke. 3.5. with <hi>Baruck</hi> 5.7.</p>
                  <p>The firſt worke of the preparing.</p>
               </note> Tranſlation of the Church the verbs thereof are rendred <hi>Imperatively;</hi> the which interpretation appeareth moſt proper, for that theſe foure matters are the duties in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall of thoſe two in generall, namely, prepare ye the way, make ye ſtraight an high way. And the firſt work of the preparing is, that every valley be exalted or filled. And a ſpirituall valley within us is want or defect of ſomewhat, which ought to be in us toward receiving revelation of the glory of the <hi>Lord.</hi> It is ſaid<note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> He that commeth unto <hi>God,</hi> muſt believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that ſeek him diligently. So that unbeliefe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be a valley, and is to be lifted up or filled up with beliefe.<note n="l" place="margin">Luke
24.25.</note> We are to believe every word of <hi>God</hi> to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect truth, according to his mind ſignified therein, though we for the preſent do not underſtand it. It is the praiſe of
<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 4.17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> that againſt hope he believed in hope, that he might become the father of many nations: according to that which was ſpoken, ſo ſhall thy ſeed be.</p>
            <p>But it was a diſpraiſe to many of the Jews, that they believed not ſundry things written in the Law of the <hi>Lord,</hi> of which unbelief <hi>Chriſt</hi> taxed them, ſaying: Had ye believed <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Joh. 5.46, 47.</note> ye would have believed me: for he wrote of me. But if ye believe not his writings, how ſhall ye believe my words? We are alſo to believe the<note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 6.7. 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. Deut. 29.19, 20.</note> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings mentioned in <hi>Gods</hi> word, aſwell as the promiſes: becauſe the
<hi>Lord</hi> is as true in the executing of them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he hath denounced them, as he is in the vouchſafing of the other.</p>
            <p>Such unbeliefe ought not to be in us, for that it is written;<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 3.18,
19.</note> The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not enter into the <hi>Lords</hi> reſt becauſe of unbelief. Another valley within man is ignorance.<note n="q" place="margin">Mat.
22.29.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid unto the Sadducees. Ye
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63618:10"/> do erre, not knowing the Scriptures nor the power of God. The <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith by <hi>Hoſea:</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6.</note> My people are deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for lack of knowledge: becauſe thou haſt rejected knowledge, I will alſo reject thee, that thou ſhalt be no Prieſt to me: Seeing thou haſt forgotten the Law of thy <hi>God,</hi> I will alſo forget thy children. Wherefore the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels commandement is to be timely conſidered viz.<note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.1, 2.</note> That we laying aſide all malice, and all guile, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſies, and envies, and evill ſpeakings; as new-borne babes to deſire the ſincere milk of the word, that we may grow thereby. Alſo not to continue ſtill<note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.20. See the Margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reading there.</note> children in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; howbeit in malice to be children; but in underſtanding to become men, perfect, or of a ripe age;
<note n="u" place="margin">Heb. 6.1. 2. Cor. 13.9. Rev. 3.2. Deut. 18.13. Gen. 6.9.</note> Going on unto perfection, as is the exhortation unto the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſaid:<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 12.48.</note> The word which I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge us in the laſt day; therefore (as ſaith the Apoſtle) let the<note n="x" place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> word of <hi>Chriſt</hi> dwell in us richly in all wiſdome.</p>
            <p>There is alſo the valley of fearfulneſſe, namely of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fearfull to begin and proceed in that, which <hi>God</hi> hath commanded to be done, and wherein he hath willed us to be<note n="y" place="margin">1. Cor. 16.13. Eph. 6.10, 13. 1. Cor. 15.58. Heb. 6.11, 12,</note> of a good courage. Such defect was in the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> being in the wilderneſſe, when as they were to have gone on couragiouſly toward the promiſed land flowing with milk and honey, in confidence of attaining poſſeſſion thereof through the help of Almighty <hi>God,</hi> they then became fearfull and faint-hearted upon reports which ſome had made, as if the ſaid land were not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable. Yea ſome ſaid,<note n="z" place="margin">Num. 13.31.</note> We be not able to go up againſt the people, for they are ſtronger then we.</p>
            <p>The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> then fell into murmuring and<note n="a" place="margin">Num.
14.2.11.12.</note> diſobedience, and ſo became to be in great perill of <hi>Gods</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63618:10"/> deſtroying of them. The <hi>Lord</hi> having ſaid in the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 21.7, 8 The ſecond worke of the preparing.</note> He that overcommeth, ſhall inherit all things, I will be his <hi>God,</hi> and he ſhall be my ſonne. But the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (namely, to enter into the ſpirituall warfare, as it is enjoyned by the Goſpel of
<hi>Chriſt</hi>) and the unbelieving, &amp;c. ſhall have their part in the lake, which burneth with fire and brimſtone: which is the ſecond death.</p>
            <p>The ſecond work of preparing is, To make low every mountain and hill. And what ſuch mountaines and hils are, it is manifeſt out of the Apoſtles words, where he ſaith: Though we walk in the fleſh,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.3, 4, 5, 6.</note> we do not warre after the fleſh: (For the weapons of our warfare are not carnall, but mighty through <hi>God</hi> to the pulling down of ſtrong holds) caſting down imaginations, and every high thing, that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and having in a readineſſe to revenge all diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, &amp;c. There is<note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.5. Job 41.34. Prov. 13.10. Iſa. 2.11, 12, 17. 2 Tim. 3.2, 5.</note> a neceſſity impoſed on us, for to ſtrive againſt all manner of pride, which the ſpirit of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> or our own fleſh and blood may raiſe up within us. It is <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſaying:<note n="e" place="margin">Mat.
18.3.</note> Except ye be converted, and become as little children, yee ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of heaven. And then afterwards ſignifieth, That we are to<note n="f" place="margin">verſe. 4.</note> humble our ſelves as they do. The <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith by
<hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakkuk:</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Hab. 2.4.</note> Behold, his ſoule which is lifted up, is not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in him. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith:<note n="h" place="margin">Ier.
48.29.11.</note> Wee have heard the pride of <hi>Moab,</hi> (he is exceeding proud) his loftineſſe, and his arrogancie, and his pride, and the haughtineſſe of his heart.
<hi>Moab</hi> hath bin at eaſe from his youth, and he hath ſettled on his lees, and hath not bin emptied from veſſell to veſſell, neither hath he gone into capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity: therefore his taſte remained in him, and his ſcent is not changed. And therefore<note n="*" place="margin">See the whole Chapter.</note> ſundry judgements are denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63618:11"/> againſt <hi>Moab.</hi> The ſpirituall mountains and hils within us, will with <hi>Divine</hi> help become laid lower and lower, if we duly conſider the doctrine of theſe Scriptures following, and of ſuch like: As,<note n="i" place="margin">1 Chron. 28.9.</note> And thou <hi>Solomon</hi> my Sonne, know thou the <hi>God</hi> of thy father, and ſerve him with a perfect heart, and with a willing minde; for the <hi>Lord</hi> ſearcheth all hearts, and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all the imaginations of the thoughts, if thou ſeeke him, he will be found of thee: but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for ever. Alſo that of S. Paul to the
<hi>Corinthians:</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10, 11.</note> We muſt all appear before the Judgement ſeate of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that every one may receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good or bad. Knowing therefore the terrour of the
<hi>Lord,</hi> we perſwade men.</p>
            <p>Moreover that ſaying of <hi>S. Peter:</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.17.</note> If yee call on the <hi>Father,</hi> who without reſpect of perſons judgeth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to every mans worke, paſſe the time of your ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing here in feare. Alſo, <hi>Davids</hi> words:
<hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 131.1, 2.</note> mine heart is not haughty, nor mine eies lofty: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I exerciſe my ſelfe in great matters; or in things too high for me. Surely I have behaved and quieted my ſelfe as a child,<note place="margin">The third worke of the preparing.</note> that is weaned of his Mother: my ſoule is even as a weaned child. The third worke of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is, to make ſtraight that which is crooked. <hi>David</hi> ſaith:<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal 125.4, 5. Phil. 2.15. Prov. 2.15.</note> Do good, O <hi>Lord</hi> unto thoſe that be good: and to them that are upright in their hearts. As for ſuch as turn aſide unto their crooked wayes, the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall lead them forth with the workers of<note n="*" place="margin">See concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning equity and iniquitie, what is ſaid in 2. Tim. 2.19. Mat. 7.7. Jſa.
16.5.12. 1 Joh. 2.29 and 3, 10.</note> iniquitie: but peace ſhall be upon <hi>Iſrael.</hi> So that crookedneſſes appeare to be a kind of works of iniquitie.</p>
            <p>Now the ten Commandements are ſaid to be the Rule of a Chriſtian life: and therefore whatſoever actions are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63618:11"/> contrary to the Morall Law contained in them, are judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be crooked;<note place="margin">1 Cor 6.9. Mat 7.22, 23. Luk 13.25, 26, 27. Jſa. 28.17. Lev. 6.2, 3, 4, 5 Pſal
119.1, 3, 6. Deut 22.1, 2, 3. Micha 6.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. Luke 19.8. Job. 20.18. Mat. 5.23,
24, 25, 26.</note> as alſo whatſoever are contrary to the ſaid Royall Law contained in any part or portion of <hi>Gods</hi> univerſall word.</p>
            <p>Moreover as all unjuſtneſſe is crookedneſſe, ſo is all unholineſſe. And therefore two Scriptures are neceſſarie to be continually remembred, unto the making ſtraight of whatſoever is crooked; namely, that of <hi>David:</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that keep judgement, and he that doth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe at<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 106.3</note> all times. Alſo that of <hi>Peter:</hi> But as he that hath called you is holy, ſo be ye holy in<note n="p" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15, 16.</note> all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of converſation, becauſe it is written: Be ye holy, for I am holy. And God is holy perpetually.</p>
            <p>The fourth work of preparing is,<note place="margin">The fourth worke of the preparing.</note> to make plaine or ſmooth the roughneſſes. And hereby is ſignified whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not<note n="q" place="margin">See Col. 1.10. 1 Joh. 3.22.</note> pleaſing to the ſpirit of Almighty
<hi>God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Luke 3.5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in planitiem. vide Lex. Buxt.</note> It is the Goſpels commandement:<note n="r" place="margin">Eph.
4.30.</note> That we grieve not the holy Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> whereby we are ſealed unto the day of Redemption.</p>
            <p>And therefore where the Apoſtle delivereth this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, hee intimateth ſundry roughneſſes to be put away, ſaying:<note n="ſ" place="margin">Verſe 31.</note> Let all bitterneſſe, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evill ſpeaking bee put away from you, with all malice. And,<note n="t" place="margin">Verſe 29.</note> Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth, but that which is good to the uſe of edifying, that it may miniſter grace unto the hearers. There is as it were a little Looking-glaſſe made by the Apoſtle, wherein every one may ſee much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſpirituall<note n="*" place="margin">Prov.
18.23.</note> roughneſſe, for to diſcern it, and to put it away: namely, in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> it being ſaid:<note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 4.9.</note> Finally, brethren, Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are<note n="*" place="margin">or venerable; as it is rendred in the margent.</note> honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63618:12"/> are of good report; if there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things: Thoſe things which ye have both learned and received, and heard and ſeen of me, doe: and the <hi>God</hi> of peace ſhall be with you.</p>
            <p>It is the ſaying of the <hi>Lord</hi> by his holy Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid:</hi> To him that<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 50.23. and 84.11.</note> ordereth his converſation aright, will I ſhew the ſalvation of <hi>God.</hi> And whereas the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly crying voice is, That every valley ſhould be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or filled up, and every mountain and hill made low, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It appeareth therefore profitable, to mention here to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſundry valleys, mountaines and hils, crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and roughneſſes, which are in divers places of the Goſpel expreſſed, to the end that whoſoever endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth preparation of the way of the
<hi>Lord</hi> within him, may perceive many of them, and may take notice of all other, whereſoever ſignified elſewhere in any place of holy Scripture. Becauſe being ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, alwaies <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <p>1. Cor. 15.58.</p>
                  <p>Valleys, mountains and hils, crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes &amp; rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up many to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuouſly, for to introduct a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout perſon to take notice of them, and of all other ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture. See 2. Eſdras. 16.50.</p>
               </note> abounding in the work of the <hi>Lord,</hi> they ſhall know that their labour is not vain in the <hi>Lord,</hi> as the Apoſtle decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth unto the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in many places of the <hi>Bible</hi> reckon up many ſuch matters together, to the end we may the more cleerly know, what qualities, conditions, properties, inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, affections, paſſions, natures, humours, infirmities, and ſuch like, we are to ſtrive againſt. All Scripture is given by inſpiration of <hi>God,</hi> and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: that the man of <hi>God</hi> may be perfect, thorowly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed unto all good works. The <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſaith.
<note n="y" place="margin">Marke 7.20, 21, 22, 23.</note> That which commeth out of the man, that defileth the man. For from within, out of the heart of men, proceed evill thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murthers, thefts,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63618:12"/> covetouſneſſe, wickedneſſe, deceit, laſciviouſneſſe, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill eye, blaſphemie, pride, fooliſhneſſe: All theſe evill things come from within, and defile the man. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith unto the <hi>Galatians:</hi> Now the works of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe,<note n="z" place="margin">Gal. 5.19, 20, 21.</note> adulterie, fornication, uncleanneſſe, laſciviouſneſſe, idolatrie, witchcraft, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, envyings, murthers, drunkenneſſe, revellings, and ſuch like, of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in time paſt, that they which doe ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of <hi>God.</hi> He writeth to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> ſaying:<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 5.3, 4, 5 6.</note> But fornication, and all unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or covetouſneſſe, let it not be once named among you, as becommeth Saints: neither filthineſſe, nor foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh talking, nor jeſting, which are not convenient: but rather giving of thanks. For this ye know, that no whoremonger, nor uncleane perſon, nor covetous one who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the Kingdome of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> and of <hi>God.</hi> Let no man deceive you with vain words: For becauſe of theſe things commeth the wrath of <hi>God</hi> upon the children of diſobedience.</p>
            <p>There is written elſewhere againſt<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 3.4, 6, 7, 8, 9. Iſa.
63.8. Rev. 21.8. and 22.15.</note> inordinate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, evill concupiſcence, all manner of lying,<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 12.9.</note> diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation<note n="d" place="margin">Rom.
1.29, 30, 31, 32.</note> debate, deceit, whiſpering, backbiting, brawling, deſpitefulneſſe, inventing of evill things, covenant-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſobedience to parents, voidnes of naturall affection, <note n="*" place="margin">See the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of Rom. 1.31.</note> unſociableneſſe, unplacablenes, unmercifulneſſe, malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, fulneſſe of envie, voidneſſe of underſtanding where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in knowledge ſhould be,<note n="e" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.2, 3, 4.</note> ſelf-love, unthankfulneſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Philemon. 19.</note> forgetfulneſſe of good turnes bodily or ghoſtly, corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Judges 9.16, 17. Wiſd. 14.25, 26. Tit. 2, 10.</note> unfaithfulneſſe, diſorders in marriages,<note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 4.24. Sirach. 16.23.</note> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon vain things, or imagining follies, falſe accuſing, incontinencie, fierceneſſe, headineſſe,<note n="g" place="margin">2. Tim.
3.2, 3, 4, 5,</note> love of pleaſure
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63618:13"/> more than <hi>God,</hi> having a forme of godlineſſe but deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the power thereof,<note n="h" place="margin">Prov. 28.4. Pſ. 15.4.</note> neglecting of loving thoſe that are good,<note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.9, 10.</note> effeminateneſſe, reviling, extortion,<note n="k" place="margin">Pſ. 15 4. So the Hebrew word there doth import. Pſ. 15.3. See alſo the margent there. Exod. 23.1. See there the Margent alſo.</note> biting uſury, <hi rend="sup">l</hi> receiving reproach againſt ones neighbour afore it be duly examined, and the truth of the report be known,<note n="m" place="margin">Prov. 8.13.</note> an evill way, a froward mouth,<note n="n" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.8.</note> uncourte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in ſpeaking or doing,<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 13.8.</note> owing any thing to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and not endeavouring according to ability for to make<note n="p" place="margin">Luke. 19.8. Mat. 18.29.</note> ſatisfaction,<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 5.37.</note> ſwearing in Communication,<note n="r" place="margin">2. Kings.
2.23, 24. Luke. 16.14.</note> mocking,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Sir 19.4. Eph. 4.14. and
3.17.</note> light-mindedneſſe,<note n="t" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.17. Ier. 23.32. Prov. 7.10,
11, 12.</note> lightneſſe in behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, in ſpeaking or doing;<note n="u" place="margin">Prov.
12.10.</note> cruelty towards man or any other creature,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 12.11.</note> ſloathfulneſſe in buſineſſe,<note n="x" place="margin">Ezech. 16.49. 2 Theſſ. 3.8, 9,
10, 11, 12.</note> idleneſſe, gluttony, not ſtrengthening the hand of the poore and needie,<note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 1.17. Pſa. 72.4. Ier. 21.12.</note> not endeavouring to help ſuch unto their right, <note n="z" place="margin">Col. 4 5. Eph. 5.15, 16, 17. Prov.
14.33.</note> miſſpending the time,<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 22.13.</note> uſing anothers ſervice without wages,<note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 25.11. 1 Pet. 4.9 Sir. 14.10</note> niggardlineſſe,<note n="c" place="margin">Jam. 1.27.</note> neglect of viſiting the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe and widowes in their affliction,<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 25.35, 36.</note> of giving meate unto the hungry, of giving drink unto the thirſtie, of hoſpitality toward ſtrangers, of clothing the naked, of viſiting and comforting the ſick what may be, of going to the impriſoned for to miniſter unto them what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is requiſite,<note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 3.15, 16. Rom. 12.11.</note> luke-warmneſſe in duties toward <hi>God</hi> or man,<note n="f" place="margin">Jam. 1.6, 7, 8. 1 Cor. 15.58.</note> unconſtancie in goodneſſe or truth,<note n="g" place="margin">Col. 3.2. Phil. 3.19.</note> ſetting ones heart on earthly things,<note n="h" place="margin">Gal 5.26.</note> provoking others unto anger,<note n="i" place="margin">Iude. 16. Gal. 4.17. Jam. 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. 1 Cor. 1.12. and 3.4.</note> overvaluing ſome and undervaluing others,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 13.7. and. 12.10.</note> not giving to every one his due honour,<note n="l" place="margin">Pſ. 50.17. Luke. 7.30.</note> hating to be inſtructed,<note n="m" place="margin">Hab. 2.6. Luke. 12.20, 21. 1 Tim. 6.10, and 3.3, 8. Eph. 5.5. Phil. 3.19, 8.</note> making it the chiefeſt care and delight to lade himſelf with thick clay, (as ſpeaketh the Prophet) viz. earthly wealth,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.23. 2 Theſſ.
1.8. 1 Pet. 4.17.</note> ſtubbornneſſe,<note n="o" place="margin">Joh. 7.49. 1 Cor. 8.1, 2. 1 Tim. 6.20, 21. Col. 2.8, 18.</note> vaunting in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63618:13"/> or hiſtoricall knowledge of holy Scripture;<note n="p" place="margin">Mal.
1.6. Lev. 19.32. Pſ. 89.7. 1 Pet. 2.17.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverence toward <hi>God</hi> or man,<note n="q" place="margin">Tit. 3.2.</note> ſpeaking evill of others, <note n="r" place="margin">1. Pet.
2.23. and 3.9. Acts. 24.14. Jam. 4.11. Gal. 5.15. Jude 9,</note> giving others reproachfull names or termes,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Deut. 16.19.</note> taking of bribes,<note n="t" place="margin">Ier. 9.23.</note> glorying in bodily ſtrength, in naturall wit, in earthly riches or worldly power,<note n="u" place="margin">Jam. 1.4. and 5.10, 11. Job. 2.9, 10.</note> unpatience,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 12.14.</note> cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,<note n="x" place="margin">Rom.
13.4. and 12.19. Acts. 4.29.</note> avenging ones ſelf when as it may be forborn, or ſhould be referred unto the Magiſtrate or Almighty <hi>God,</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 5.7 Zech.
7.10.</note> oppreſſion,<note n="z" place="margin">Jonah. 3.8. Zeph. 3.4.</note> violence,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.6. See Margent.</note> over-reaching another in any matter,<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 20.7. Sirach.
23.9, 10.</note> mentioning lightly the name of <hi>God</hi> or any of his word, not endeavouring to have in continuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance His preſence,<note n="d" place="margin">Luke. 6.27.</note> not ſhewing due love to ones ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,<note n="e" place="margin">Pro. 10.12.</note> diſcovering of others infirmities,<note n="f" place="margin">Prov. 11.13. and 17.9.</note> revealing of ſecrets which may lawfully be concealed,<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 7.12. Luke 6.31.</note> not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring in every particular to do unto another, as he would have another to do unto him,<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.7. Jam. 5.5. 2 Pet. 2.13. 1 Pet. 4.3, 4.</note> ſitting downe to eate and drink, and riſing up to play, not having a due fellow-feeling of others<note n="*" place="margin">Amos. 6.6. 1 Cor. 12.25, 26.</note> ſufferings,<note n="i" place="margin">1 Joh.
5.21. Eze. 14.3, 4, 7.</note> all worſhipping of idols outward or inward,<note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 58.9. Mat. 12.36, 39.</note> ſpeaking of vanitie,<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 33.15.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding any evill with delight, not abſtaining from<note n="m" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.22.</note> all appearance of evill, giving<note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.32.</note> offence unto any,<note n="o" place="margin">Joſ. 22.12, 16, 18,
19, 20.</note> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of offence upon no juſt ground,<note n="p" place="margin">Eccles. 5.2. Pſ.
112.5.</note> raſhneſſe,<note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 2.4.</note> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely to the good of ones own ſelf,<note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 6 4. Gen. 18.19.</note> neglect of edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating children and ſervants unto the learning and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all the Goſpels commandements,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Tit. 3.14. See the margent there. 1 Cor. 7.24. 1 Pet. 2.12. Deut.
16.20.</note> neglect of ſtudying the duties of ones particular vocation, an<note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 8.2. and 12.3. and. 3.18. 1. Tim. 6 3, 4.</note> high eſteeming of ones own conceived knowledge in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all matters afore he be truly regenerate, a<note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 2.3. 1 Pet. 2.17. 2 Cor. 8.12. Mat. 22.39.</note> ſetting light of any others gifts how ſmall ſoever, which he endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth well to uſe;<note n="*" place="margin">Lev.
26.21. See the margent there.</note> Proceeding in any matter at all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63618:14"/> adventures, and not endeavouring to have <hi>Gods</hi> Word for<note n="x" place="margin">Prov. 3.5, 6, 7. Iſa. 8.20. Pſ. 119.9. Gal. 6.10.</note> rule in every action,<note n="y" place="margin">Luke. 14.41.</note> neglect of almes giving, neglect to learn and practiſe<note n="z" place="margin">Rev. 3.3. Pſ. 119.6.</note> every chriſtian vertue, or to become more and more a new creature in the<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.17. Rev. 21.5. 1 Theſſ. 5.23. 2 Cor. 4 16. Prov. 4.18.</note> whole inward man, and in the outward converſation.</p>
            <p>The holy Scripture diſcovereth very many more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, exceſſes, enormities, and imperfections in the mind and life of mankind, all which<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Ier. 7.5. Lament 3.40. 2 Eſdras. 16.50. Prov. 22.6. Joh. 4.23.</p>
                  <p>The fourth point, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit which now commeth to the true pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parers, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the crying voices preſcription. Foure things to bee conſidered in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the fourth point.</p>
               </note> throughly to ſearch out it is our bounden duty, yea to begin from our very youth this worſhipping of <hi>God</hi> in ſpirit and in truth.</p>
            <p>The fourth point is the benefit, which now commeth in a true endeavour to performe the aforeſaid preparation. The Text ſaith: And the glory of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and all fleſh ſhall ſee it together.</p>
            <p>Now unto the underſtanding hereof there are foure things to be conſidered. Firſt, what the glory of the <hi>Lord</hi> here mentioned is. Secondly, where it ſhall be revealed. Thirdly, who ſhall behold it. And fourthly, in what manner it ſhall be ſeen.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, what the glory of the <hi>Lord</hi> is, which is here promiſed to be now revealed unto ſuch, as prepare a way for the <hi>God</hi> of<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ.
135.2. Eph. 2.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> to have an habitation within them, it is manifeſt out of S. <hi>Luke</hi> to be meant the eternall <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> For the Evangeliſt hath expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the promiſe with theſe words: And all fleſh ſhall ſee the<note n="c" place="margin">Luke. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Salvation</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> By which name <hi>Salvation Simeon</hi> alſo called <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where he ſaith:<note n="d" place="margin">Luke. 2.30,
31, 32.</note> For mine eyes have ſeen thy <hi>Salvation,</hi> which thou haſt prepared before the face of all people: a Light to lighten the Gentiles, and the glory of thy people
<hi>Iſrael.</hi> For <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> according to His eternall Divine Nature is the ſupreame heavenly light,<note n="e" place="margin">Joh. 10.30.</note> equall with <hi>God</hi> his Father. The Apoſtle expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63618:14"/> him to be the<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 1.3. Wiſd. 7.26.</note> brightneſſe of the <hi>Fathers</hi> glory. And it is written in S. <hi>John,</hi> That he is the true light<note n="g" place="margin">Joh. 1.9.</note> which lighteth every man that commeth into the world. Who alſo in every age paſt hath according to His <hi>Godhead</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in ſome manner unto holy ſoules, as <hi>Micah</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, where he ſaith:<note n="h" place="margin">Micah. 5.2.</note> Whoſe goings forth have bin from of old, from the dayes of eternitie.</p>
            <p>And concerning the ſaid ſpirituall comming for to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue whiles the world doth endure, our <hi>Saviour</hi> Himſelf alſo teſtifieth, ſaying:<note n="i" place="margin">Joh.
14.23.</note> If any man love me, he will keep my words; and my <hi>Father</hi> will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him. The Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Godhead of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is by an ancient<note n="k" place="margin">Juſtinus Martyr in dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo cum Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phone Judaeo.</note> Father thus declared: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That is, In the beginning (or, firſt of all) afore all creatures <hi>God</hi> begate out of his own ſelf a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rationall <hi>Vertue</hi> (or reaſonable <hi>power</hi>) which alſo is called by the Holy Ghoſt the Glory of the
<hi>Lord,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a <hi>Sonne,</hi> ſometimes Wiſdome, ſometimes an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, ſometimes <hi>God,</hi> ſometimes the <hi>Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Word.</hi> Moreover here by the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> there may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood alſo the Image of the glorious
<hi>God,</hi> conſiſting in godly underſtanding, righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe. The Apoſtle ſaith: All have ſinned, and come ſhort of the<note n="l" place="margin">Rom.
3.28.</note> glory of <hi>God,</hi> or of his image. And therefore he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth, That we put on that new man, which after<note n="m" place="margin">Eph. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe: and is renewed in knowledge,<note n="n" place="margin">Col. 3.10.</note> after the image of him that created him.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is ſaid by <hi>God:</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Num. 14.21.</note> As truly as I live, all the earth ſhall be filled with the glory of the <hi>Lord.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:<note n="p" place="margin">Hab. 2.14.</note> The earth ſhall be filled with the knowledge of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63618:15"/> the glory of the <hi>Lord,</hi> as the waters cover the Sea. And in another place:<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 11.9.</note> The earth ſhall be full of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Lord,</hi> as the waters cover the Sea. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all<note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor.
2.10. See all <hi>Baruch</hi> 5.</note> knowledge of <hi>God</hi> and his will revealed in his word, may here be included alſo, that it ſhall be more and more revealed unto his obedient people.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond thing to bee conſidered.</note>Secondly, There is to be conſidered, where the glory of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall be revealed according to this promiſe. And whereas it immediatly followeth, That all fleſh ſhall ſee it together, it appeareth that the ſaid Revelation is within man. The Apoſtle ſaith:<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gal. 1.15,
16. See concerning the Myſterie of <hi>God</hi> in man, Wiſ. 7.22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27,
28.</note> When it pleaſed <hi>God,</hi> who ſeparated me from my mothers wombe, and called me by His grace, to reveale His <hi>Sonne</hi> in me, that I might preach Him among the Heathen, &amp;c. And afterward he ſaith: They glorified <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">verſe
24.</note> in me. To the <hi>Romanes</hi> hee writeth: For I reckon that the ſufferings of this preſent time, are not worthy to be compared with the glory which ſhall be revealed<note n="*" place="margin">Rom.
8.18.</note> in us. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo intimateth it, where he ſaith:<note n="v" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19.</note> untill the <hi>Day-ſtarre</hi> ariſe in our hearts. Which
<hi>Starre</hi> truly is the glory of the <hi>Lord, Chriſt</hi> according to His Divine nature, as Himſelf ſaith: I <hi>Jeſus</hi> am the bright and Morning<note n="*" place="margin">Rev.
22.16.</note> ſtarre. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo ſignifieth where the Revelation of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> is, in that counſell given unto women, concerning whom he ſaith:<note n="x" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning let it be the hidden man of the heart. It is in the <hi>Syrian</hi> Text: Adorne your ſelves with the <hi>Sonne</hi> of man the hidden one of the heart. And that <hi>Chriſt</hi> becomes to be within his people, according to his Spirit, is often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the writings of the Apoſtles. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the Corinthians:<note n="y" place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5. Col. 1.27.</note> Know ye not your own ſelves, how that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is in you, except ye be reprobates? The Goſpel teacheth, that
<hi>God</hi> the<note n="z" place="margin">Eph. 4, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Father</hi> is in his people, likewiſe <hi>God</hi> the<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Sonne,</hi> and alſo
<hi>God</hi> the<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.19. and 3.16. and 2. Cor. 6.16. Rom. 8.9,
11.</note> 
               <hi>Holy Ghoſt:</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:63618:15"/> Hence it is ſaid:<note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 45.13.</note> The Kings daughter is all glorious within.<note n="d" place="margin">Luke. 17.21.</note> The Kingdome of
<hi>God</hi> is within us.<note n="e" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, hath ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of <hi>God,</hi> in the face of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is thirdly to be conſidered,<note place="margin">The third thing to be conſidered.</note> Who ſhall behold this glory of the <hi>Lord.</hi> The words of the Text are, All fleſh. And this is not meant concerning univerſall humane fleſh, but only of that, which beareth in it the true <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> the fear of the <hi>Lord.</hi> It is ſaid in
<hi>Ezechiel;</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezechiel.</hi> 36.26.</note> I will give you an heart of fleſh. And the <hi>Chaldee</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation there is to this effect,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Et dabo vobis c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtimens coram me ad facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum voluntatem meam.</note> That it is ſuch an heart as is in awe of <hi>God,</hi> and is inclined to do his will.</p>
            <p>Alſo in a moſt ancient booke of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> there is a ſaying concerning what preſently followeth circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which being underſtood of the circumciſion of the heart, is a very memorable ſentence:</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Zohar.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> That is: Wee have learned, that at what time ſoever, wherein a ſonne of man ſhall be marked with the holy ſignature of this ſigne; from thence he after ſome manner ſeeth <hi>God,</hi> and the holy ſoul becommeth united with him. But <hi>Chriſts</hi> words do make the matter plain, where he ſaith: He that hath my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me: and he that loveth me ſhall be loved of my <hi>Father,</hi> and I will love him, and<note n="h" place="margin">Joh. 14 21.</note> manifeſt my ſelf unto him: So that ſaying unto the true
<hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> Ariſe, be enlightned, for thy light is come, and the<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 60.1, 2.</note> glory of the <hi>Lord</hi> is riſen upon thee. For behold, the darkneſſe ſhall cover the earth, and groſſe darkneſſe the people, but the
<hi>Lord</hi> ſhall ariſe upon thee, and his glory ſhall be ſeen on thee. S. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63618:16"/> the matter, ſhewing how <hi>God</hi> is perceived by his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſaying:<note n="k" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.18.</note> But we all with open face, beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of the <hi>Lord,</hi> are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the <hi>Lord.</hi> A ſoule<note n="l" place="margin">Ezech. 18.21.</note> repenting for all the ſinnes which it hath committed, and<note n="m" place="margin">Luke.
13.24.</note> ſtriving to obſerve obediently<note n="n" place="margin">Pſ. 119.6. Luke.
1.6.</note> all <hi>Gods</hi> everlaſting commandements,<note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 3.23. Heb
10.36, 37.</note> at length attaineth to have a<note n="p" place="margin">Phil. 1.9. See the Margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reading. Heb. 6.4, 5.</note> feeling of the holy Spirit working<note n="q" place="margin">Eph. 3.20. Col. 1.29.</note> within it: and the<note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 1.18. The fourth thing to bee conſidered.</note> eye of the underſtanding being enlightned, it perceiveth what is the hope of His calling, and what are the riches of the glory of His inheritance in the Saints.</p>
            <p>The fourth matter to be conſidered, is the manner or (if it may be ſo expreſſed) poſture, wherein all ſhall ſee the revealed Glory of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which labour in the worke of due preparing the way of the <hi>Lord</hi> into them. And it is ſaid, Together. But the Hebrew word there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſeemeth to import aſmuch as to ſay<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Schindlers Lexicon <hi>and</hi> Buxtorfs Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxis.</note> 
               <hi>Every one toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Alſo the ſame word in a certain Pſalme is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted for to ſignifie
<hi>Unity;</hi> as where it is ſaid:<note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 133.1.</note> Behold, how good and how pleaſant it is, for brethren to dwell together in unity. Whereas therefore the promiſe is, that all truly holy ones ſhall ſee together or in unity, it declareth that <hi>Gods</hi> revealing of his heavenly light ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth unto Unity, unto the bringing of all and every one of them into Chriſtian unity of minde and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and alſo into uniformity of life and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely, to be more and more of the mind and life of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is written:<note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 2.5. 1 Cor. 2.16.</note> Let this mind be in you, which was in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And it is alſo written:<note n="*" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.6.</note> He that ſaith, he abideth in him, ought himſelf alſo ſo to walk, even as he walked. And to endeavour for to be in ſuch Unity was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63618:16"/> the profeſſion of the ancient ones in the houſe of <hi>God,</hi> as it may appear from what is ſaid, namely: Walked wee not in the<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor.
12.18.</note> ſame Spirit? Walked we not in the ſame ſteps? Yea alſo S. <hi>Luke</hi> recordeth,<note n="y" place="margin">Acts. 4.32.</note> That the multitude of them which believed, were of one heart, and of one ſoule. It is the promiſe of <hi>God</hi> to bleſſe his obedient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the ſpirit of Unity. He ſaith: And I will give them<note n="z" place="margin">Jer. 32.39.</note> one heart, and one way, that they may feare me for ever, for the good of them, and of their children af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them. He ſaith alſo:<note n="a" place="margin">Jer.
31.33, 34</note> I will put my Law in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, and write it in their hearts, and I will be their <hi>God,</hi> and they ſhall be my people. And they ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, Know the <hi>Lord:</hi> for they ſhall all know me, from the leaſt of them unto the greateſt of them, ſaith the <hi>Lord.</hi> Alſo ſaith
<hi>Chriſt:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 17.22.</note> And the glory which thou gaveſt me, I have given them, that they may be one, even as we are one.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, as there is<note n="c" place="margin">Zeph. 3 9. Zech. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Jer. 32.39. 2 Cor. 12.18.</note> Unity in obſerving the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Morall Law contained in the Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements; ſo is there alſo Unity in the moſt holy<note n="d" place="margin">Jude 10. Tit. 1.1.</note> faith of <hi>Gods</hi> elect. The Apoſtle ſaith, There is<note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 4.5.</note> one faith. And he hath theſe words:<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 4.13.</note> Till we all come into the Unity of faith, and of the knowledge of the <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And as all which truly endeavour to make preparation of the way of the <hi>Lord</hi> within them, according as it is preſcribed by the aforeſaid heavenly crying voice, ſhall ſee more and more the<note n="g" place="margin">1 Tim.
3.9.</note> myſterie of the Chriſtian faith, and what the true Chriſtian<note n="h" place="margin">Joh. 8.12. Mal. 4.2. See <hi>wiſd.</hi> 5.6.</note> life and converſation is, unto the increaſe of godly Unity; ſo ſuch as are<note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 4.3.</note> ſtudious of all holy Unity, ſhall partake of the greateſt meaſure of heavenly light, which
<hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63618:17"/> now communicateth unto his ſervants. It is ſaid in the Booke of
<hi>Chronicles:</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2 Chron. 5.13, 14.</note> It came to paſſe, as the trumpetters and ſingers were as one, to make one ſound to be heard in praiſing and thanking the <hi>Lord:</hi> and when they lift up their voice with the trumpets and cymbals, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of muſick, and praiſed the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaying, For he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever: that then the houſe was filled with a cloud, even the houſe of the
<hi>Lord.</hi> So that the Prieſts could not ſtand to miniſter, by reaſon of the cloud: for the glory of the <hi>Lord</hi> had filled the houſe of <hi>God.</hi> So it is ſaid in the
<hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles:<note n="l" place="margin">Acts 2.1, 3, 4,</note> And when the day of
<hi>Pentecoſt</hi> was fully come, they were all with one accord (or, with one mind) in one place. And there appeared unto them cloven tongues like as of fire, and it ſate upon each of them; and they were all filled with the Holy Ghoſt. Then did <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Acts 2.16, 17, 18.</note> powre out of his Spirit upon all fleſh; namely, on all ages and ſtates, as on old perſons and young perſons, on ſonnes and daughters, on ſervants and hand-maids: and in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance on his Apoſtles, who had<note n="n" place="margin">Acts. 1.4.</note> waited for the promiſe, and had kept in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Which (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) is builded as a City, that is<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal.
22.3.</note> compact together; or, (as ſome tranſlate) which is at unity in it ſelf. For where brethren dwell together in unity,<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 133.3. Where there is ſuch concord: us ſaith the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> note. The Ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</note> there (ſaith he) the <hi>Lord</hi> commandeth the bleſſing, even life for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>There remaineth alſo, that ſomething be ſaid concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Ratification of this Oracle, which is contained in theſe words, For the mouth of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſpoken it. The which words are added for to aſſure us, That our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the work of the Lord ſhall not now be in<note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.51.</note> vain, our true endeavouring for to performe the aforeſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration ſhall not be unconſidered. For <hi>God</hi> (ſaith the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63618:17"/> Apoſtle) is not unrighteous to<note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 6.10, 11, 12,
13, 14, 15. Mat. 10.41, 42. Pſ. 19.11. Heb. 11.26.</note> forget your work, and labour of love, which ye have ſhewed toward His name, &amp;c. And we deſire that every one of you doe ſhew the ſame diligence, to the full aſſurance of hope unto the end: That ye be not ſloathfull, but followers of them, who through faith and patience inherit the promiſes. For when <hi>God</hi> made promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe he could ſweare by no greater, He ſware by Himſelf, ſaying, Surely, bleſſing I will bleſſe thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee. And after he had patiently endured, he obtained the promiſe.</p>
            <p>Whereas it is ſaid, For the mouth of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſpoken it, it giveth us to conſider, that a mouth hath uttered it, which<note n="ſ" place="margin">Tit. 1.2.</note> cannot lye; and that the Almighty, holy, &amp; righteous eternall <hi>Spirit</hi> hath promiſed it, which is<note n="t" place="margin">Eph. 3.20.</note> able to performe it: Who hath promiſed many ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to be inherited in the life that<note n="u" place="margin">1. Tim.
4.8.</note> now is: according as His Divine power hath given unto us all things, that pertain unto life and godlineſſe, through the knowledge of him (as S. <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.3, 4.</note> ſaith) that hath called us to glory and vertue: whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promiſes, that by theſe ye might be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Divine Nature, having eſcaped the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is in the world through luſt. That (as the Apoſtle writeth unto the<note n="x" place="margin">Eph. 1.12, 13, 14.</note>
               <hi>Epheſians</hi>) We ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the praiſe of his glory, who firſt truſted in
<hi>Chriſt:</hi> in whom ye alſo truſted, after that ye heard the word of truth, the Goſpel of your Salvation: in whom alſo after that ye believed, ye were ſealed with that holy Spirit of promiſe, which is the earneſt of our inheritance, untill the redemption of the purchaſed poſſeſſion, unto the praiſe of his glory. And as the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſaith:<note n="y" place="margin">Mar. 10.29, 30.</note> There is no man that hath left houſe, or brethren, or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63618:18"/> ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my ſake and the Goſpels, but he ſhall receive an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold now in this time, houſes, and brethren, and ſiſters, and mothers, and children, and lands, with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions; and in the world to come eternall life.</p>
            <p>Moreover, it is to be obſerved, that theſe words <hi>[for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it]</hi> being ſo often uſed in holy Scripture,<note place="margin">What the mouth of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſignifieth.</note> do in ſpeciall manner note forth unto us the power and truth of <hi>God,</hi> upon which we may build, and ground our ſelves, and be ſecure or<note n="z" place="margin">See of Heb. 11.1. the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall reading</note> confident, that what duties we for our parts are to endeavour, are<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 19.7, 8. Deut. 4.6, 7, 8.</note> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect wiſdome to be done, and that the benefit ſignified to be received in the doing of them, is moſt ſure and certain. It is ſaid in <hi>Ezechiel:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ezech. 37.13, 14.</note> And ye ſhall know that I am the <hi>Lord,</hi> when I have opened your graves, O my people, and brought you up out of your graves: And ſhall have put my Spirit in you, and ye ſhall live, and I ſhall place you in your own land: then ſhall ye know that I the <hi>Lord</hi> have ſpoken it, and performed it, ſaith the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to conclude this point, there is obſerved to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by theſe words [The mouth of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſpoken] Such a more inward manifeſting and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating of the Divine will, as whereby matters were made knowne unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> as it is written: With him will I ſpeak<note n="b" place="margin">Num. 12.8.</note> mouth to mouth apparently. For ſo
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not out of his own mind this crying voice; (as <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> ſaith, That the falſe Prophets doe ſpeak a viſion of their own heart,<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 23.16.</note> and not out of the mouth of the <hi>Lord</hi>) but it being preſented unto him by <hi>God,</hi> he received it; and having received it, wrote it in his prophecie.</p>
            <p>Alſo hence (as was afore noted) the truth and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Divine promiſe is ſhewed, That <hi>God</hi> who hath promiſed to reveale his heavenly and ſpirituall light, unto
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63618:18"/> every perſon truly repenting according to the crying voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces doctrine, will performe it ſo as it may be ſeen of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one in the<note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 4.3. Acts.
2.1, 2, 3, 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ab</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>unanimis; ex</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſimilis, idem, &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>animus, quibus eſt idem animus, Paſor.</hi> Mat. 18.19, 20. Pſ. 89.5.</note> unity of the holy Spirit of the
<hi>Lord.</hi> And an example of all may be that in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, That when ſome which had been ſpirituall wilderneſſes and deſarts, &amp; had heard <hi>Peters Sermon,</hi> they were<note n="e" place="margin">Acts. 2.37, 38, 41, 42, 44, 46.</note> prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their hearts, and ſaid unto <hi>Peter,</hi> and to the reſt of the Apoſtles, Men and brethren, what ſhall we do? Then <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto them, Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for the remiſſion of ſinnes, and yee ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt. Then they that gladly received his word, were baptized: And they continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles doctrine and fellowſhip, and in breaking of bread, and in prayers. And all that believed, were together, and had all things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. And they continuing daily with one accord in the Temple, and breaking bread from houſe to houſe, did eate their meate with gladneſſe, and ſingleneſſe of heart, praiſing
<hi>God,</hi> and having favour with all the people.</p>
            <p>Now alſo having by Divine aſſiſtance thus explained the afore-mentioned Fundamentall portion of holy Scripture, there are to be declared Seven Uſes,<note place="margin">Seven Uſes, whereunto the heavenly cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voice is profitable. The firſt uſe is unto Doctrine.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto it is profitable. And the firſt is unto Doctrine. For this heavenly crying voice teacheth, that every one of mankind is under one of the three ſpirituall ſtates ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Oracle; namely, under Deſolation, Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Revelation. Whiles one is a wilderneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, he is in the ſtate of deſolation: when one beginneth and proceedeth in<note n="f" place="margin">1. Joh. 3.3. Ier. 4.14. Iſa. 1.16.</note> purifying of himſelf, he is then in the ſtate of preparation: and he that hath the Glory of the
<hi>Lord</hi> revealed unto him in ſome meaſure and manner, is in the ſtate of Revelation.</p>
            <p>Concerning the two firſt ſtates there is no doubt made.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63618:19"/> Onely queſtion is about the third mentioned ſtate.<note place="margin">Queſtion or doubt onely is about the third mentioned ſtate.</note> And that there is ſuch a diſtinct condition ſpirituall, it may appeare out of theſe Scriptures following. S. <hi>Paul</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth concerning ſome of the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> and
<hi>Epheſians,</hi> that which is to the ſame effect, where he writeth, ſaying:<note n="g" place="margin">Col 1.12, 13.</note> Giving thanks unto the <hi>Father,</hi> which hath made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light: who hath delivered us from the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and hath tranſlated us into the Kingdome of his deare <hi>Sonne.</hi> He hath<note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 1.3.</note> bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in heavenly places in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">and 2.6,</note> He hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together in heavenly places in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus. David</hi> at laſt entred hereinto, when as hee ſaid: Returne into thy<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal.
116.7, 8, 9.</note> reſt, O my ſoule, for the <hi>Lord</hi> hath dealt bountifully with thee. For thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered my ſoule from death, mine eyes from teares, and my feet from falling. I will walke before the <hi>Lord</hi> in the land of the living. It is ſaid in the Apoſtle unto the <hi>Hebrewes:</hi> We which have believed<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 4.3.</note> do enter into reſt. <hi>S. Paul</hi> attained at length to ſay:<note n="m" place="margin">2 Tim.
4.7.</note> I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith. For they which fight manfully againſt ſinne, the world, and the Devill, do through the Divine Spirit<note n="n" place="margin">Phil 4.13. Rom. 8.13.</note> ſtrengthning them,<note n="o" place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4, 5</note> beate down and overcome vice, ſo as that ſinne<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> raigneth not in their mortall body, that they ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof: but through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="q" place="margin">Luke
1.71, 74, 75.</note> delivered out of the hand of all enemies, they ſerve <hi>God</hi> without feare, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him all the daies of their life. The ſaid third ſtate is the<note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.11. and 14.20.</note> manly age in
<hi>Chriſt:</hi> It is that which they enjoy, whom <hi>S. John</hi> calleth<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 John. 2.13, 14, 20, 27. 1 John 1.3, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Fathers. It is that ſtate, wherein <hi>God</hi> is in ſome meaſure found and injoyed. A place in the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> maketh it plain, where it is ſaid: It was but a little
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63618:19"/> that I paſſed from them,<note place="margin">Some at length in this world doe attaine to find <hi>God,</hi> and to enjoy him in ſome meaſure, and manner.</note> but I<note n="t" place="margin">Can. 3.1, 2, 3.4 Iſa. 55 6. Ier. 29.13, 14.</note> found Him whom my ſoule loveth: I held him, but I would not let him goe, untill I had brought him into my mothers houſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the chamber of her that conceived me. A time was, when <hi>Job</hi> ſaid concerning <hi>God:</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Job. 9.11.</note> Loe, He goeth by me, and I ſee him not: he paſſeth on alſo, but I perceive him not. But at length he attained to ſay:<note n="*" place="margin">Job. 42.5.</note> I have heard of thee by the hearing of the eare: but now mine eye ſeeth thee. It is ſaid in the book of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> That<note n="x" place="margin">1 Chron. 26.5. See the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall reading there.</note> 
               <hi>Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi> had underſtanding in the viſions of <hi>God.</hi> It is alſo written that <hi>S. Steven</hi> being full of the Holy Ghoſt, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up ſtedfaſtly into heaven, and<note n="y" place="margin">Acts. 7.55, 56.</note> ſaw the Glory of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſtanding on the right hand of <hi>God,</hi> and ſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I ſee the heavens opened, and the <hi>Sonne of man</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the right hand of <hi>God.</hi> And ſuch a ſpirituall ſight hee had, whiles hee was living in His body, ſome certaine time afore his death. It is teſtified concerning <hi>Zacharias</hi> and
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> his wife,<note n="z" place="margin">Luke. 1.6.</note> That they were both righteous before <hi>God,</hi> walking in all the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ordinances of the
<hi>Lord</hi> blameleſſe.<note place="margin">The ſecond uſe for Refutation.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond Uſe is for Refutation of opinion in many, who think that their minds can be well enough now, without endeavouring as this heavenly crying voice pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth. And therefore they will not<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 10.4, 6. Pſ. 14.1. &amp;c. Job. 21.14, 15. and 22.17. Mal.
3.14. Wiſd. 2.21. See all Wiſd. 2. For it deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, what the minde and life of Atheiſts is.</note> meddle with any ſuch meditation. Can the ſoule of any one be in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſtate, which continueth a wilderneſſe or deſart, having the<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor.
2.12. 2 Cor. 4.4. Eph. 2.2. 2 Tim. 2.25, 26. Luke 11.21, 22 24.</note> ſpirit of the World
<hi>(Satan)</hi> reigning with his power therein? The Apoſtle ſaith:<note n="c" place="margin">Rom 6.16.</note> Know ye not, that to whom ye yeeld your ſelves ſervants to obey, his ſervants ye are, to whom ye obey? Can ſuch be in a ſafe condition, which will paſſe their time (as the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi rend="sup">d</hi> without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> being aliens from the common-wealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers from the covenants of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63618:20"/> promiſe, having no hope, and without <hi>God</hi> in the world? Hath not
<hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid, But thoſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould<note n="e" place="margin">Luke. 19.27.</note> reigne over them (or have my kingdome of grace<note n="f" place="margin">Luke. 17.21. The third uſe for correction.</note> within them) bring hither and ſlay them before me.</p>
            <p>A Third uſe is for Correction of moſt perſons, which paſſe their time in this world, not minding this one ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary thing, namely, to bee now an habitation for the mighty
<hi>God</hi> of <hi>Jacob.</hi> O what paines do moſt take all their life long, ſome in one humane<note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 9.23, 24.</note> learning, ſome in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; ſome in the<note n="h" place="margin">Pſ. 39.6. Hab. 2 6.</note> getting or<note n="i" place="margin">1. Tim.
6.10. Luke. 12.19.</note> loving of worldly wealth, ſome in following their own<note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.7. 2. Tim. 3.4. Job. 21.13. See the margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reading there.</note> earthly pleaſures; others in<note n="l" place="margin">Col. 3.2. Phil. 3 19. The <hi>Summum Bonum</hi> in this world.</note> ſetting their hearts on other matters, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſeverall affections, and neglect the <hi>Summum Bonum</hi> the Soveraigne or Supreme good in this preſent world, to wit, the<note n="m" place="margin">1. Joh. 1.3, 4. and 4.16, 17. Eph. 3.19. and
4.13. Song. 3.4. Joh. 14.21, 23.</note> enjoying of <hi>Gods</hi> gracious preſence within ones ſoule,<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 5.22. Micah. 6.8.</note> walking with <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.17. Joh. 17.21.</note> joyning to the <hi>Lord,</hi> and becomming one ſpirit with him. The Apoſtle ſaith:<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> If any one have not the Spirit of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hee is none of his. Of whoſe Spirit the fruit is<note n="q" place="margin">Gal. 5.22, 23, 24.</note> love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, temperance: and it is in<note n="r" place="margin">Eph.
5.9.</note> all goodnes and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and truth. They which are wholly for<note n="ſ" place="margin">Col. 2.8. Acts 17.18.</note> humane learning, or for the<note n="t" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5. Mat. 23.2, 3. and 5.20. Ier. 22.16, 17. 1 Joh. 2.3, 4. Gen. 3.6.</note> meere hiſtoricall knowledge of what is contained in <hi>Divine writ,</hi> that they may proceed ſo farre therein as is poſſible, and do make ſuch under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their glory, and endeavour to have it for the greateſt contentment of the minde, are not in the right, they have not the<note n="u" place="margin">Prov. 9.10. Job. 28.28. Pſ. 111.10. and 119.98, 99, 100.</note> perfect wiſdome. For it is the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels doctrine:<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.1, 2. See the <hi>Geneva</hi> Tranſlation of 1. Cor. 13.2. and the Greeke Text.</note> Though I ſpeake with the tongues of men and of Angels, and have not charity, I am become
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63618:20"/> as ſounding braſſe, or a tinkling Cymball. And though I have the gift of
<hi>prophecie,</hi> and underſtand all myſteries, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, ſo that I could remove mountains, and have not Charity, I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. It is ſaid alſo elſe where:<note n="x" place="margin">1. Joh. 4.7, 8 8, 16. Deut. 4.6, 7, and 32.29. and 5.29. 1 Cor. 8.3. Joh. 15.10, 14.</note> Let us love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for love is of <hi>God:</hi> and every one that loveth, is borne of <hi>God,</hi> and knoweth <hi>God.</hi> He that loveth not, knoweth not <hi>God,</hi> for <hi>God</hi> is love. <hi>God</hi> is love, and he that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> in him. And what the ſaid lovers nature and properties are, it is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed in the thirteenth chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to the
<hi>Corinthians,</hi> where ſixteen qualities thereof are reckoned up, that there may be no miſtake concerning the charity or love, which the holy Goſpell preſcribeth and requireth.<note place="margin">The fourth uſe for inſtruction.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A fourth uſe is for Inſtruction; That ſeeing our <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> willeth, that we<note n="z" place="margin">Pſ. 119.166, 174. 1 Pet. 1.13, 14, 15. 1 Theſſ. 1.10. 1. Cor. 1.7,
9.</note> zealouſly endeavour the aforeſaid preparation, and then waite for the Revelation there promiſed; that we<note n="a" place="margin">Jer. 7.5. Lam. 3.40. Conſider the importance of the Hebrew Text. See <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation thereof</note> throughly ſearch and try our waies, and turne home quite unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> maketh exhortation. Wherewithall (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) ſhall a young man<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 119.9. 2 Cor. 13.5. 1 Theſſ. 5.21, 22.</note> cleanſe his way? By taking heed thereto, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy word.</p>
            <p>We are therefore to conſider all the word of the <hi>Lord,</hi> for to ſee what valleys, mountaines and hils, crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and roughneſſes it doth diſcover to be in us, that ſo with help of his holy Spirit, we may put them all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way more and more. We are alſo often to pray as <hi>David</hi> did:<note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 63.1, 2, 8. Wee are to pray continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for <hi>Gods</hi> helpe hereunto.</note> O <hi>God,</hi> Thou art my <hi>God,</hi> early will I ſeek thee: My ſoule thirſteth for thee, my fleſh longeth for thee in a dry and thirſtie land, where no water is; to ſee thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and thy glory, ſo as I have ſeen thee in the Sanctuarie. My ſoule followeth hard after thee.<note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 143.10. and
25.5.</note> Teach me to doe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63618:21"/> thy will, for thou art my <hi>God,</hi> Thy Spirit is good: leade me into the Land of uprightneſſe.<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 43.3.</note> O ſend out thy light and thy truth, let them lead me, let them bring mee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy holie Hill, and to thy Tabernacles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſaid worke of preparation is not to bee deferred.</note>Moreover, the ſaid worke of preparing a way for the <hi>Lord</hi> to come into us, is not to be deferred untill old age, or untill there be perill of death or of ſome great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; but as the Holy Ghoſt ſaith:<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 3.7, 8, 13, 15.</note> To day if yee will hear his voice, harden not your hearts as in the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the day of temptation in the wilderneſſe. The Apoſtle there ſaith: Exhort one another daily, whiles it is called to day, leſt any of you be hardned through the the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne. Continuall obſervation decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a certain counſell to be wholeſome, which ſaith:<note n="f" place="margin">Sirach. 5.7. Deut.
29.10, 21. Rom. 2.4, 5, 6. Pſ. 119.59, 60. 1 Theſſ. 5.2, 3. <hi>Maledictus qui florem juventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſuae diabolo, et faecem ſenectutis Deo reſervat, Auguſtinus.</hi>
               </note> Make no tarrying to turn unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> and put not off from day to day: for ſuddenly ſhall the wrath of the <hi>Lord</hi> come forth, and in thy ſecuritie ſhalt thou be deſtroyed, and periſh in the day of vengeance.<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 55.6.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith: Seeke ye the <hi>Lord,</hi> while he may be found, call ye upon him, while he is neere.
<hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith:<note n="h" place="margin">Luke. 13.25, 26, 27.</note> When once the maſter of the houſe is riſen up, and hath ſhut to the doore, and ye begin to ſtand without, and to knock at the door, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Lord, Lord;</hi> open unto us, and he ſhall anſwer, and ſay unto you, I know ye not whence ye are: Then ſhall ye begin to ſay, Wee have eaten and drunken in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and thou haſt taught in our ſtreets. But hee ſhall ſay, I tell you, I know you not whence you are; depart from me all ye workers of iniquitie.
<hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith:<note n="i" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.6.</note> They ſhall go with their flocks, and with their heards to ſeeke the <hi>Lord:</hi> but they ſhall not finde him, hee hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne himſelfe from them. Wherefore the counſell written by <hi>Ieremiah</hi> is ſtill to be conſidered, to wit:<note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 6.8.</note> Bee thou inſtructed,
<hi>O Jeruſalem,</hi> leſt my ſoule depart from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63618:21"/> thee: leſt I make thee deſolate, a land not inhabited.<note place="margin">The fift uſe is unto patience.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A fift Uſe is unto patience, which (as S. <hi>James</hi> ſaith)<note n="l" place="margin">Jam.
1.4.</note> ought to have her perfect work, that we may be perfect and entire, wanting nothing. The Apoſtle ſaith unto the <hi>Hebrewes:</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 10.36, 37.</note> Ye have need of patience, that after ye have done the will of <hi>God,</hi> ye might receive the promiſe. For yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry. S.
<hi>James</hi> alſo ſaith:<note n="n" place="margin">Jam. 5. 7,8.</note> Be patient there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, brethren, unto the comming of the <hi>Lord:</hi> behold, the husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, untill he receive the early and the latter raine. Be ye alſo patient, ſtabliſh your hearts: for the comming of the <hi>Lord</hi> draweth nigh. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith unto <hi>Timothy:</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.3, 11,
12,</note> Thou therefore endure hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as a good ſouldier of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is a faithfull ſaying: If we be dead with him, we ſhall alſo live with him. If we ſuffer, we ſhall alſo reign with him. There muſt be a time of<note n="p" place="margin">Ier.
4.3, 4. Hoſ. 10.12. Micah. 4.3. 2. Tim. 2.6. See the margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reading there.</note> plowing, ſowing and weeding, afore there can be a time of reaping and mowing. He ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the
<hi>Hebrewes:</hi> Let vs<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 12.1, 2.</note> lay aſide every weight, and the ſinne which doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and let us runne with patience the race that is ſet before us, looking unto <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Author and Finiſher of our faith; who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the croſſe, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand of the throne of <hi>God.</hi> Who alſo ſaith: To him that<note n="r" place="margin">Rev. 3.21.</note> overcommeth, will I grant to ſit with me in my throne, even as I alſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came, and am ſet down with my <hi>Father</hi> in his Throne.</p>
            <p>A ſixt uſe is unto Comfort.<note place="margin">The ſixt uſe is unto conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> If we lay to heart that whole crying voice, and faithfully endeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the foure preſcribed works of preparation; though preſently from wilderneſſes and deſarts we become not ſuch gardens and paradiſes, as we ought to be; yet let us
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63618:22"/> remember the counſell of the Apoſtle:<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Joh. 8 Heb. 10.35.</note> Looke to your ſelves, that we looſe not thoſe things which we have wrought, but that we receive a full reward. <hi>God</hi> Almighty will ſtretch forth his<note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 118.14, 15, 16. and 17.7. 1 Pet. 5.10.</note> right hand over us, hee will ſtay us up and ſtrengthen us. I will (ſaith the <hi>Lord</hi>)<note n="u" place="margin">Pſ.
32.8.</note> inſtruct and teach thee in the way which thou ſhalt go: I will guide thee with mine eye: For (ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall comfort <hi>Sion:</hi> He will comfort all her waſte places, and he will make her<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 51.3. and
31.15, 16, 17, 18. The Seventh uſe of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly crying voice is to ſhew the way unto true Chriſtian unitie, among all rightly fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>God. Concordia ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemur, diſcordia peſſum imus. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonymus.</hi>
               </note> wilderneſſe like <hi>Eden,</hi> and her deſart like the garden of the <hi>Lord:</hi> joy and gladneſſe ſhall be found therein, thankeſgiving and the voice of melody. The prophet hath written even a whole chapter, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the five and thirtieth, for the conſolation of ſuch as do prepare the way of the <hi>Lord</hi> into them.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh uſe of the ſaid Oracle is, to ſhew the way unto Chriſtian Unity, among all that truly feare <hi>God.</hi> But among ſome of mankind Unity cannot be: for ſaith the Apoſtle,<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14, 15.</note> What fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with unrighteouſneſſe? and what communion hath light with darkneſſe? And what concord hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Belial?</hi> Or what part hath he that believeth, with an unbeliever? <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith: An unjuſt man is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the juſt: and he that is<note n="y" place="margin">Prov. 29.27. See Sirach 13.15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. Prov.
13.10.</note> upright in his way, is abomination to the wicked. He alſo ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 28.4. Who bee the true fearers of <hi>God.</hi>
               </note> They that forſake the Law, praiſe the wicked: but ſuch as keep the Law, contend with them. Moreover, all are not true fearers of <hi>God,</hi> which ſay that they are right fearers of Him. And therefore it is to be mentioned, whom only the Scripture ſignifieth to feare <hi>God</hi> rightly and truly.
<hi>David</hi> ſaith:<note n="z" place="margin">Pſa. 119.1. See the ancient Tranſlation of the Church, as alſo the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> Text. See Sirach. 2, 15, 16, 17.</note> Bleſſed is the man that feareth the <hi>Lord,</hi> he delighteth greatly in his commandements. That is the ſure and certain marke, whereby every true fearer of <hi>God</hi> may be diſcerned from all other perſons. Alſo <hi>Solomon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63618:22"/> what is the feare which <hi>God</hi> accepteth, where he ſaith:<note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 8.13.</note> The feare of the <hi>Lord</hi> is to hate evill: pride, and arrogancie, and the evill way, and the froward mouth do I hate.</p>
            <p>Now among all ſuch endued with ſuch feare of <hi>God,</hi> there is poſſibilitie of<note n="b" place="margin">1 Joh. 5.1, 2, 3. 2 Joh. 1.2. Pſ. 119.63, 74. Luke. 15.7, 10.</note> Chriſtian Unitie, and that they will<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 11.12, 13. and 25.7,</note> embrace whatſoever may further them unto agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the truth of the <hi>Lords</hi> holy word, and unto the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in all godly love. And although among many, which in a<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.1, 3. What is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by <hi>God</hi> ſhall bee, ought not to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted unpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. Zech. 14.9.</note> good meaſure make conſcience of their wayes, there is ſo great difference in underſtanding and affection, as that it is by ſome conceived impoſſible, that they may by any meanes come into an holy concord; yet a ſaying of Chriſt may be thought on, which is:<note n="e" place="margin">Luke. 18.27.</note> The things which are unpoſſible with men, are poſſible with <hi>God.</hi> It is<note n="f" place="margin">Ezech.
37.1. &amp;c.</note> written that <hi>Ezechiel</hi> was ſet in the midſt of a valley full of dry bones: and it was ſaid unto him, can theſe bones live? And hee anſwered, <hi>O Lord God,</hi> thou knoweſt. But he prophecying as he was commanded, there was a noiſe, and behold a ſhaking, and the bones came<note n="g" place="margin">verſe 7. In the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the church, in Pſ. 68.6. There is read: Hee is the God, that maketh men to bee of one minde in an houſe.</note> together, bone to his bone. There was then a great beginning of Unitie.</p>
            <p>Let us moſt ſeriouſly conſider, what ſaith the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crying voice, That the Glory of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto all preparers of his way, and they ſhall ſee it together: for the mouth of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſpoken it, who hath power to performe, whatſoever he promiſeth. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith elſewhere:<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa.
54.13,</note> All thy children ſhall be taught of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and great ſhall be the<note n="i" place="margin">The ſaid word in ſenſe impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Unity.</note> peace of thy children. Great unitie will be among all thoſe, which are led by his holy Spirit and Word, for his Spirit leadeth into all<note n="k" place="margin">Joh. 16.13. Acts. 5.32. Eph. 4.3. 1 Cor.
12.13.</note> truth ſuch as unfeinedly ſtrive to yeeld due obedience unto all the commandements of <hi>Chriſts</hi> holy Goſpel. The wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63618:23"/> of the <hi>God</hi> of heaven made uſe of this<note n="l" place="margin">Ier.
8.22.</note> Balme of <hi>Gilead</hi> (the crying voice) when great difference was in the Church of the <hi>Jewes:</hi> and it with his Divine<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6.</note> bleſſing cured a great many. It was <hi>John</hi> the<note n="n" place="margin">Luke. 3.3, 4, 5, 6.</note> Baptiſts doctrine: yea<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 4.17. Mar. 1.14, 15. Luke. 4.18, 19.</note>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his<note n="p" place="margin">Mar. 6.12. Acts. 20.21. Luke. 13.3, 5.</note> Apoſtles in effect did uſe it in their preaching. O into what an unitie it brought the true fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of <hi>God,</hi> which were in<note n="q" place="margin">Acts. 2.1, 38, 41, 42, 46,
47.</note> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the land of <hi>Jewrie!</hi> And ſo how it wrought among the Gentiles, witneſſe all the<note n="r" place="margin">Col. 2.1, 2, 5.</note> Churches of them unto whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles wrote Epiſtles: Alſo the ſame efficacie by the aſſiſtance of Divine grace, will it now take among all ſuch, as will make due uſe of it, as it did in thoſe daies of old. For ſaith the Scripture, Behold, the <hi>Lords</hi> hand is not<note n="ſ" place="margin">Iſa. 59.1, 2.</note> ſhortened, that it cannot ſave, neither his eare heavie, that it cannot heare. But your<note n="t" place="margin">Ier. 5.25. Pſ. 66.18.</note> iniquities have ſeparated between you and your <hi>God,</hi> and your ſinnes have hid his face from you, that he will not heare. The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid:<note n="u" place="margin">Luke. 1.51.</note> He ſcattereth the proud in the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of their hearts. But his <hi>Sonne</hi> gathereth together into<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 11.52.</note> one the children of <hi>God,</hi> that are ſcattered abroad, as even <hi>Caiphas</hi> propheſied. Yea unto Unitie worketh <hi>God</hi> the
<hi>Father, Sonne,</hi> and Holy Ghoſt;<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <p>Eph. 1.10. It is to bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, That as in the beginning man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in unity with <hi>God;</hi> ſo Holy Scriptures uſe is to direct us for to draw nigher and nigher unto the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> prayed ſo fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently for his people concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their true Chriſtian unity See Joh. 17.11, 21, 22, 23.26.13.</p>
               </note> That (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) in the diſpenſation of the fulneſſe of times, he might gather together in one all things in
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> both which are in heaven, and which are on earth, even in Him.</p>
            <p>Moreover, that the receiving of heavenly light into the underſtanding doth further unto unitie, it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare from a ſimilitude. If a company be in a dark room, where is very little light, and it hath a table whereon is much mony,<note place="margin">A Similitude for to ſhew, that the true heavenly light, whereſoever it appeareth, doth further unto true Chriſtian unitie.</note> gold and ſilver, and ſome counterfeit coine
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63618:23"/> be among the ſame; If they be willed to take only all the currant mony, and thereunto to adviſe each with other for the better judging of the ſame; and alſo be promiſed increaſe of benefit, according as every one taketh moſt of the ſaid coin with none of the counterfeit. Will there not ariſe ſome difference among them, concerning ſome pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the mony? Will there not be ſome conjectures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, becauſe they judge for the moſt part by ſuppoſing or imagination, &amp; not by clear ſight? But if a window be opened unto them, and they have the true day light, will not then the caſe be otherwiſe, and all former diſſent in opinion about the ſaid coine much ceaſe? So is it with us mankind: ſo long as we abide faſt in the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 60.2. Ier. 4.22, 23.
1 Joh 2.9, 11.</note> groſſe darkneſſe covereth us, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſignifieth. Yea S. <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that they were ſometime<note n="z" place="margin">Eph. 5.8. Prov. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And the Prophet alſo ſpeaking concerning ſuch, ſaith:<note n="a" place="margin">Iſ. 59.10.</note> We grope for the wall like blind, and we grope as if we had no eyes: we ſtumble at noone-day as in the night, we are in deſolate places as dead men. The<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of
<hi>God,</hi> for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him: neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned. The <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> ſaith: The<note n="c" place="margin">Joh.
14.17. 1 Joh. 5.19. 2 Cor. 4.4.</note> Spirit of truth the world cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him. Great is our ſpirituall darkneſſe, manifold are our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes about the things of <hi>God.</hi> Yea alſo we much differ in opinion concerning ſuch matters. But when as we heare the heavenly<note n="d" place="margin">In Iſa 40.3, 4,
5.</note> crying voice, and attend thereunto; when we open the<note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 3.20. Pſ. 24.7, 8, 9, 10.</note> door of our hearts, and receive the <note n="f" place="margin">Eph.
3.16, 17. 1 Cor. 14.25. Gal. 2.20. Col. 3.11. and 1.27. 2. Cor. 13.3.</note> Spirit of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> thereinto, He will then<note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 5.14. 2 Cor. 4.6. 2 Pet.
1.19. Prov. 28.5. Phil. 1.9, 10, 11. Pſ. 112.4.</note> give us light; he will open unto us ſuch a ſpirituall window, and let ſuch a meaſure of true heavenly light ſhine into us, as that we ſhall judge more and more rightly concerning all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63618:24"/> things pertaining unto Godlineſſe. Alſo former differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among us will more and more ceaſe, and the unitie of the Holy Spirit will inwardly and outwardly among us encreaſe.<note place="margin">Another Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude for to ſhew, how a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong all well-affected, the true Chriſtian unitie eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Heare alſo another ſimilitude. Even as in an houſhold, where all the ſervants do faithfully mind the performing of every command of their maſter, and one to help ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the fulfilling of the ſame, will there be any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſion among ſuch? Or if any ſhould chance through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſtake, will it not ſoon ceaſe, for that none ſeeketh himſelf, but every one onely his maſters benefit and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit? So among all thoſe, whoſe<note n="*" place="margin">The mind of mankind for the farre great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part, hath as it were loſt it ſelfe, in that it conſidereth not the marke which the Creatour hath preſcribed unto it.</note> only aime it is, that our heavenly Maſters will may be done here on earth,<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 6.10. Rom. 12.2. Eph. 5.17. 1 Theſſ. 4.3, 4, 5, 6.7.</note> as it is in heaven; and<note n="*" place="margin">The ſaid marke, at which to aime continually, and whereon to mind al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in every particular mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is in briefe ſignified in the afore quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Mat.
6.10. Eph. 5 17.</note> thereunto do endeavour what may be, to help and ſet forward one another, will there be any diſcord among ſuch? Or if any difference doth chance, will it not ſoon be compoſed, when as none ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owne honour or by-reſpects, but only the honour and glory of <hi>God;</hi> None the doing of his owne will and mind, but only the doing of <hi>Gods</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Deut. 29.29. Acts. 13.22. Joh. 1.12, 13. 1 Pet. 4.1, 2. Mat. 3.15. Col.
1.25.</note> revealed will in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing.</p>
            <p>Such fellow-ſervants will ſtill remember, What is enjoyned by the Goſpel, where it is ſaid:<note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 6.1, 2. See Phil. 2.1, 2, 3.</note> Brethren, if any man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpirituall, reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſſe, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted. Beare ye one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burdens, and ſo fulfill the Law of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now heare ſome cauſes, why ſuch difference is among ſome zealous perſons, And the ſaying is; That when cauſes do ceaſe, the effects will ceaſe more and more. It is a great cauſe of difference, where there is minded but <note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. Cauſes of difference among many religious perſons. The firſt mentioned cauſe.</note>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:63618:24"/> part of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Goſpel, and not the whole. Many onely mind what
<hi>Chriſt</hi> hath done for us; but nothing or very little what he<note n="m" place="margin">Mat.
23.23. Micah. 6.8. Rom. 8.12, 13. Mat. 5.20. Rom. 8.4. Luke. 13.3, 5. Mat. 18.3. Luk. 14.26, 27,
33. Job. 3.5, 6. and 12.24, 25, 26.</note> requireth to be done by us. It is true, we ought to learn every particular matter mentioned in any holy Scripture, concerning what the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath done for his Church, and to underſtand the ſame according to the mind of
<hi>God.</hi> But withall we are alſo to learn every particular duty, which is taught in any place of the holy Goſpel, and with helpe of his holy ſpirit to ſtrive for to perform every of the ſame.<note n="n" place="margin">Joh. 15.14.</note> Saith not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you? Did he not charge his Miniſters to teach all nations, for to obſerve<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 28.20.</note> all things, whatſoever he hath commanded? Is not he the Prophet to be heard in<note n="p" place="margin">Acts. 3.22, 23.</note> all things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he ſhall ſay unto us?<note n="*" place="margin">In all ages there hath bin much unitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which have aſwell minded every duty in life and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the Goſpel preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, as the matters which it ſignifieth to bee beleeved.</note> It is ſtill obſerved, that there is much unitie among all ſuch, as mind aſwell what the Goſpel teacheth to be done, as what is to be believed: but among ſuch as mind only points of faith, and do neglect the matters concerning life and converſation preſcribed therein, the diſcord is much and manifold. It is written, that the Angel of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid unto the Apoſtles:<note n="q" place="margin">Acts. 5.20. Joh. 10.10. and 12.50.</note> Go, ſtand and ſpeak in the Temple to the people all the words of this life. Which giveth us to underſtand, that true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity for a great part conſiſteth in matter of life and converſation. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſaith:<note n="r" place="margin">Jam. 1.27</note> Pure Religion, and undefiled before <hi>God,</hi> and the Father, is this, To viſit the fatherleſſe and widowes in their affliction, and to keepe himſelf unſpotted from the world. The<note n="*" place="margin">It is in the ancient larger notes called the Geneva ones See 1 Cor.
4.20. Rom. 14.17. Rom. 2.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 13. 1 Joh. 3.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>Geneva</hi> note thereon is: The true ſervice of <hi>God</hi> ſtandeth in charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our neighbours (eſpecially ſuch as need others help, as the fatherleſſe and widowes) and purity of life. The <hi>parentheſis</hi> being left out, the ſentence is: The true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>God</hi> ſtandeth in charity toward our Neighbours,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63618:25"/> and purity of life. <hi>Micah</hi> ſaith:<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <p>Micah 6.8. See the margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reading there: alſo the <hi>Geneva</hi> Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of that verſe. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned cauſe of difference.</p>
                  <p>Whereas many take no notice of the benefits, which the Scripture ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, that the truly godly doe enjoy now in the body, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their ſoules and mindes, hence is it, that they hope for no ſuch ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bleſſings now, neither endeavour the preſcribed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for them. And ſo ſetting not the ſaid ſpirituall marke before them, for to aime thereat, &amp; to approach neerer and neerer unto it, they come not into ſuch a comfortable meaſure of Chriſtian uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as others doe. See Job. 22.21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29. And the marginall readings there. See 2 Cor. 6.16, 17, 18. and 27.1. Rev. 2.7, 17, 26, 27, 28. and
3.5.12.</p>
               </note> He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth the <hi>Lord</hi> require of thee; but to do juſtly, and to love mercie, and to<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor.
6.17.</note> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſelf for to walk with thy <hi>God..</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another cauſe of ſo much difference is, That many bear not in mind the marke, at which they ſhould now aime, and hope for to attain unto in this life and world: For the Apoſtle ſignifieth, That Godlineſſe hath aſwell promiſes, benefits and bleſſings<note n="t" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> now to be enjoyed, beſides what hereafter unto all eternitie. And for that thoſe ſpirituall comforts are not now preſſed hard after, minds become divided and<note n="u" place="margin">Ier. 50.6. Iſa. 53.6.</note> ſcattered farre apart. If archers go forth to ſhoote, and every one ſhooteth which way ſoever he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventureth, their arrowes do commonly fall down farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part: but if they all doe aime at one and the ſame marke, then are they all found about the mark, though ſome nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to it than other. It is a mark whereat we ſhould now aime, to be joyned<note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 2.6. ſheweth an high degree in Chriſtian unitie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſome of the <hi>Epheſians</hi> had through Divine grace then attained</note> unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> and ſo to become one ſpirit with him, as farre forth as he now vouchſafeth unto his ſervants; If then I, thou, he, and innumerable more become ſo one ſpirit with him, what diſcord can long continue between us then? The neglect therefore of the ſtudy of attaining now Union with <hi>Gods</hi> holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is a cauſe of ſo much variance among many, which yet notwithſtanding have ſome good affections and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable beginnings. But all Wordlings bear the mind of<note n="x" place="margin">Num. 23.10.</note> 
               <hi>Balaam.</hi> They would willingly die the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ones, and that their laſt end be like theirs; but whiles they live in bodily health and outward proſperity, they are willing to retain within them the ſpirit of the world,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63618:25"/> and to<note n="y" place="margin">Acts 7.51.</note> ſhut out of their hearts the ſpirit which is of <hi>God.</hi> They conſider not on that ſaying of the Goſpel:<note n="*" place="margin">If wee would have our ſoules long to proſper in our bodies, let us not now ſhut out of our ſoules God the Spirit of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly light and of heavenly love. Prov. 8.31.</note> If any one have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is none of his. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Solomon</hi> ſignifieth; That <hi>Chriſts Spirit</hi> now on earth dwelleth in his gardens, as it is written:<note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 8.13. The third men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned cauſe of difference, which ceaſing, true Chriſtian concord will daily increaſe.</note> Thou that dwelleſt in the Gardens, the companions hearken to thy voice: cauſe me to heare it.</p>
            <p>The third cauſe (and that a great one) why there is ſuch difference in affection among many, is becauſe that, which our <hi>Creatour</hi> (bleſſed for ever) hath ordained to be the bond and tie of his people together,<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> is by many neglected or not duly indeavoured; and that is Charity, namely, the Charity which the Goſpel hath expreſly delivered. The Apoſtle ſaith unto the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> having exhorted them unto ſundry great vertues:<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 3.14. 2 Theſſ. 1.3. 1 Theſſ.
3.12.</note> Above all theſe things put on Charity, which is the bond of perfectnes. And if it is the bond and tie of the higheſt matters in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, is it not likewiſe the bond and tie of all inferiour matters therein,<note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 4.15, 16. Col. 2.19. Heb. 10.24, 25.
1 Theſſ. 2.7, 8. Joh. 13.34, 35. 2 Joh. 6.</note> That from the very Infancie in
<hi>Chriſt</hi> there may bee a comfortable growing up unto the eldeſt age, which is in Him and through Him. If the ſheaves of a field bee not tied up together, how can they bee well brought home into the barne? So among whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the ſaid bond or tie ordained by the eternall
<hi>Wiſdome,</hi> is not put on, how can there bee a good growing up together into the Chriſtian unitie? S. <hi>Paul</hi> declared it to bee his great<note n="d" place="margin">Or conflict. See the margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reading of Col. 2.1.</note> care; even for all profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſtianity, That their hearts might bee comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being<note n="e" place="margin">Col. 2.2. And in verſe 5. hee ſheweth the power or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the ſaid knot, ſaying: Though I bee abſent in the fleſh, yet am I with you in the ſpirit, joying and beholding your order, and the ſtedfaſtneſſe of your faith in Chriſt.</note> knit together in love, &amp;c. Hee giveth it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for a rule for every particular action in this world, where he ſaith: Let all your things be done with<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.14.</note> chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63618:26"/> And hereon ſaith <hi>D. Lucas Oſiander,</hi> that famous Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:<note place="margin">Sixteen proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Charity expreſſed in 1 Cor. 13.4, 5, 6.7, 8.</note>
               <hi>Omnium actionum noſtrarum moderatrix debet eſſe chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> Charity ought to be the moderatreſſe (or ruler) of all our actions. The Holy Ghoſt thus deſcribeth charitie, ſaying: Charity ſuffereth long, and is kind: charity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieth not: charity vaunteth not it ſelf (or, is not<note n="g" place="margin">So is the marginall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of 1 Cor. 13.4.</note> raſh,) is not puffed up, doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, ſeeketh not her own, is not eaſily provoked, thinketh no evill, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth not in iniquity, but rejoyceth in (or,<note n="h" place="margin">So is it in the marginall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. See 1 Pet. 4.8. Prov. 10.12. Song 8.6, 7.</note> with) the Truth. Beareth (or, <hi rend="sup">i</hi> covereth) all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things. Charitie never faileth. There is delivered lately concerning chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that which is very conſiderable, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>In page 67. of the booke intituled,</hi> The nature of Truth its union and unitie with the ſoule. Printed anno
<hi>1641.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Doth not the Apoſtle, doth hee not moſt truly, moſt pathetically cry out? Though I had the gift of prophecie, and knew all ſecrets, all knowledge, yea, if I had all faith, ſo that I could remove moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, I were nothing; I were as ſounding braſſe, and a tinkling Cymball, if I have not charitie. When all theſe excellencies meet in a Chriſtian, as haply they may; yet it is charity that maketh him</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">See
1 Joh. 4.7, 8.12, 16. and 1 Cor. 13.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>what he is, and the other beeings are but as phalerae, as trappings which give an handſome ſet off, but not a being to a Chriſtian.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">In page 68. of the aforeſaid booke.</note> 
               <hi>Love is lovely in Gods eye, He is ſtiled the God of Love, the God Love. And in another place, the Scripture affirmeth, that in this we have fulfilled the will of God, if wee love one another; for by</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <p>Here is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by union with <hi>God</hi> is, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to 1 Joh. 4.16.</p>
                  <p>The fourth mentioned cauſe of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>this we are made one with God, and ſo dwell in true light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt cauſe, which ſhall be mentioned at this preſent, why there is ſo much difference among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, is, for that ſo few have any care at all to underſtand their own way; and that the moſt addict themſelves to judge one anothers way. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſaith: The wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the prudent is to<note n="o" place="margin">Prov. 14.8.</note> underſtand his way.<note n="p" place="margin">Verſe. 12.</note> There is a way that ſeemeth right unto a man: but the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63618:26"/> are the waies of death.<note n="q" place="margin">Prov. 12.15.</note> The way of a foole is right in his own eyes: but hee that hearkeneth unto counſell is wiſe. <hi>David</hi> ſaid:<note n="r" place="margin">Pſ. 119.24. See The margent there.</note> Thy Teſtimonies are my delight, and men of my counſell. Now the counſell of the eternall Wiſdome is, That whoſo would be a Diſciple of <hi>Chriſt</hi> or a true Chriſtian, he do firſt of all betake himſelfe to<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 7.5.</note> caſt out the beame out of his own eye; becauſe then he ſhall ſee cleerly to caſt out the mote out of his brothers eye. Alſo to<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 16.24.</note> deny himſelf. To become a<note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.18.</note> foole, that he may be wiſe. To<note n="*" place="margin">Luke. 14.26, 33.</note> hate his own life, and to forſake all that he hath (all his <hi>Laodicean</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Rev. 3.17, 18.</note> riches.) To follow <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 19.28.</note> Regeneration: To<note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note> judge nothing before the time, untill the <hi>Lord</hi> come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſſe, and will make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the counſels of the hearts: and in his particular<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 14.23.</note> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall comming will guide into<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 16.13.</note> all truth. To doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing through ſtrife or vain-glory, but in lowlineſſe of minde each to<note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 2.3.</note> eſteem other better than themſelves; and not to think every one to be in the wrong, which differeth from him concerning ſome ceremoniall matter or the like. To ſhun all<note n="d" place="margin">2 Tim.
3.2.</note> ſelf-love.<note n="e" place="margin">Ezech 36.31. and 20.43. See. 2. Cor. 7.11.</note> To remember ones owne evill wayes, and his own doings that were not good, and to loth himſelfe in his own ſight for his iniquities, and for his abominations. To conſider that the<note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 17.9.</note> heart is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full above all things, and deſperately wicked: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to<note n="g" place="margin">Prov. 4.23.</note> keep it with all diligence. Not to<note n="h" place="margin">Prov. 3.5, 6, 7.</note> leane unto ones own underſtanding: but in all ones wayes to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>Lord,</hi> and he will direct ones paths. Not to be wiſe in ones own eyes: but to feare the <hi>Lord,</hi> and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from evill. To<note n="i" place="margin">Jam. 1.26. Iſa. 58.9. Mat. 12.34, 36, 37. Eph. 5.4, 5, 6.</note> bridle ones tongue: becauſe his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is vain, and not the true Chriſtian, which doth not unfeinedly endeavour that dutie; as the Holy Ghoſt hath pronounced. Now when as one hath duly judged his<note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.31.</note>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:63618:27"/> own ſelf by <hi>Gods</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſa. 119.9. 2 Tim. 3.16,
17. Rom. 15.4.</note> univerſall word, and underſtood his<note n="m" place="margin">Iſa.
53.6.</note> own way to be not right, Then will he pray with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid:</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſ. 139.23, 24.</note> Lead mee in the way everlaſting. For in walking in that<note n="o" place="margin">Ier. 6.16.</note> old path, that good way, (wherein all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and people of <hi>God</hi> ſince the Creation have walked, there commeth reſt unto ones ſoule. Hee will alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with <hi>Paul,</hi> that of ſinners hee is<note n="p" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15.</note> cheife. Hee will<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 18.33.</note> have compaſſion on his fellow-ſervant, even as the <hi>Lord</hi> hath had pity on him. Hee will not pray for<note n="r" place="margin">Luke 9.54, 55, 56.</note> fire to come downe from heaven, for to conſume every one that doth not preſently receive <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Goſpels commandement: The ſervant of the <hi>Lord</hi> muſt not ſtrive; but be<note n="ſ" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.24, 25, 26.</note> gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient: In meekneſſe, inſtructing thoſe which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves, if <hi>God</hi> peradventure will give them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to the acknowledging of the truth: And that they may recover themſelves out of the ſnare of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, who are taken captive by him at his will. Alſo to<note n="t" place="margin">Tit. 3.2, 3. 1 Pet. 2.17.</note> ſpeak evill of no man, to be no brawler, but gentle, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all meekneſſe unto all men. For wee our ſelves alſo were ſometimes fooliſh, diſobedient, deceived, ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures, living in malice and envie, hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and hating one another. Alſo to<note n="u" place="margin">1 Theſſ.
3.12.</note> pray for to increaſe and abound in love one towards another<note n="*" place="margin">Due notice is to bee taken of this Duty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the holy Goſpel.</note> and towards all men, even as did the Apoſtles towards the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> He will then continually think upon that great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Law and Goſpel, that<note n="*" place="margin">James. 2.8. Gal. 5.14. Rom. 13.8, 9, 10.</note> Royall Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">What here followeth is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to bee underſtood, ſo as it may make againſt no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Law of <hi>God.</hi> It is meant concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ones bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring at leſt to live in all common ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility. But if any one doe contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſword is to bee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. See Rom. 13.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> To have a care to work none ill unto ones neighbour, but unfeinedly to wiſh, and to endeavour (what may be) that all good, and all comfort, and all content may come unto him, which one would unto his own ſelf, in every particular caſe of this preſent world. He will then ſee, that every one void
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63618:27"/> of the charity, which the Goſpel preſcribeth and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, (or doth not truly endeavour unto the<note n="x" place="margin">Col. 3.14.</note> putting on of the ſame) is not in the Right. For the Holy Ghoſt pronounceth: He that ſaith he is in the light, and hateth his brother,<note n="y" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.9, 11.</note> is in darkneſſe even untill now. He that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his brother, is in darkneſſe, and walketh in darkneſſe, and knoweth not whither he goeth, becauſe that darkneſſe hath blinded his eyes. He that loveth not,<note n="z" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.8.</note> knoweth not <hi>God,</hi> for <hi>God</hi> is love.<note n="a" place="margin">verſe 20.</note> If any man ſay I love <hi>God,</hi> and hateth his brother, he is a liar. For he that loveth not his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whom he hath ſeen, how can he love
<hi>God</hi> whom he hath not ſeen? The holy Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> ſaith:<note n="b" place="margin">Mal. 2.10.</note> Have we not all one Father? Hath not one <hi>God</hi> created us? Why doe we deale treacherouſly every man againſt his brother, by prophaning the covenant of our Fathers? He will then lay to heart that great ſaying of the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> viz. The<note n="c" place="margin">Joh. 12.48.</note> word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge him in the laſt day. And therefore he will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider of theſe and the like ſayings of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; which <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.3.</note> ſpake in them, as; Who art thou that<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 14.4.</note> judgeſt another mans ſervant? to his own maſter he ſtandeth or falleth. Yea, he ſhall be holden up: for
<hi>God</hi> is able to make him ſtand.<note n="f" place="margin">Verſe 10.</note> Why doeſt thou judge thy brother? Or why doeſt thou ſet at nought thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgement ſeate of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Verſe. 12.</note> Every one of us ſhall give account of himſelf to <hi>God.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Verſe.
13.</note> Let us not therefore judge one another any more, but judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling block, or an occaſion to fall in his brothers way.<note n="i" place="margin">James.
4.11, 12. Gal. 5.15.</note> Speak not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill one of another (brethren:) He that ſpeaketh evill of his brother, and judgeth his brother, ſpeaketh evill of the Law, and judgeth the Law: but if thou judge the Law, thou art not a doer of the Law, but a Judge. There is one
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63618:28"/> Law-giver, who is able to ſave, and to deſtroy: Who art thou that judgeſt another? Alſo what <hi>David</hi> delivereth, viz. Unto the wicked <hi>God</hi> ſaith:<note n="k" place="margin">Pſ. 50.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22.</note> What haſt thou to do to declare my ſtatutes, or that thou ſhouldeſt take my covenant in thy mouth; Seeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteſt my words behind thee. When thou ſaweſt a theife, then thou conſentedſt with him, and haſt bin partaker with adulterers. Thou giveſt thy mouth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and thy tongue frameth deceit. Thou ſitteſt and ſpeakeſt<note n="*" place="margin">The Goſpel requireth, that wee duely ſpeake againſt our owne ſelves. 1 Cor.
11.31. Mat. 7.5. Luke. 6.41, 42. Lam. 3.40. 2 Cor. 13.5. and 2. Cor. 7.10, 11. 1 Tim. 1.15. Luke.
15.18, 19, 21. Exod. 23.1. Eph. 4.31. Pſ. 15.3. See <hi>Sirach.</hi> 19.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Deut.
27.24. James. 1.26.</note> againſt thy brother, thou ſlandereſt thine owne mothers ſonne. Theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilence: thou thoughteſt that I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelfe: but I will reprove thee, and ſet them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before thine eyes. Now conſider this, ye that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <hi>God,</hi> leſt I tear you in pieces, and there bee none to deliver. Let us therfore no more<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 23.24.</note> ſtraine at a gnat, and ſwallow a Camell. Let us ever remember that ſaying of the Holy Ghoſt:<note n="m" place="margin">1 Joh. 3.15.</note> Whoſoever hateth his brother, is a murtherer. Alſo what the
<hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the righteous Judge hath pronounced, viz.<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 5.22.</note> Whoſoever is angry with his brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and whoſoever ſhall ſay to his brother, <hi>Racha,</hi> ſhall be in danger of the Councill: but whoſoever ſhall ſay, thou foole, ſhall be in danger of hell-fire. I will forewarn you (ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi>) whom ye ſhall feare:<note n="o" place="margin">Luk. 12.5.</note> Feare him, which after he hath killed, hath power to caſt into Hell, yea I ſay unto you, Feare Him. Wherefore in reverence and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 12.28, 29.</note> feare of our <hi>God,</hi> which is a conſuming fire,<note n="q" place="margin">Eph. 4.1, 2, 3.</note> let us (according to the Apoſtles exhortation) walke worthy of the vocation wherewith we are called, with all lowlineſſe and meekneſſe, with long ſuffering, forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in love, endeavouring to keep the unity of the
<hi>Spirit</hi> in the bond of peace. Let us be<note n="r" place="margin">Eph 2.20, 21, 22. 1 Pet.
2.5. See the margent there.</note> built upon the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63618:28"/> of the Apoſtles and Prophets, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> Himſelfe being the chief corner ſtone: in whom all the building fitly framed together, groweth unto an holy Temple in the <hi>Lord.</hi> Let us<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.18 Iſa. 65.18, 19. Iſa.
66.10, 11.12, 13, 14.</note> comfort one another with the words of the <hi>Lord,</hi> concerning the great Unitie, peace and concord, foretold to come to paſſe in this laſt Time.
<hi>God</hi> ſaith by <hi>Zephaniah:</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Zeph. 3.9.</note> For then will I turn to the people a pure lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, that they may all call upon the name of the <hi>Lord,</hi> to ſerve him with one conſent. He ſaith by <hi>Jeremiah:</hi> I will give them<note n="u" place="margin">Ier. 32.39. Ezech. 11.19.</note> one heart, and one way, that they may feare me for ever, for the good of them, and of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren after them. <hi>Zechariah</hi> ſaith:<note n="*" place="margin">Zech. 14.9.</note> The <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall be a King over all the earth: in that day ſhall there be one Lord, and his name one. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith:<note n="x" place="margin">Jſa. 16.5.</note> And in mercie ſhall the Throne be eſtabliſhed, and be ſhall ſit upon it in truth, in the Tabernacle of <hi>David,</hi> judging and ſeeking judgment, and haſting righteouſneſſe. He ſaith elſe where: The<note n="y" place="margin">Jſa. 11.6, 7, 8, 9. Jſa. 65.25. alſo Jſa. 25.6, 7,
8.30.26.24.23.11.11.12.11.13.</note> wolfe alſo ſhall dwell with the lambe, and the leopard ſhall lie down with the Kid: and the calfe, and the young lion, and the fatling together, and a little child ſhall leade them. And the cow and the beare ſhall feed, their young ones ſhall lie down together: and the lion ſhall eate ſtraw like the oxe. And the ſucking child ſhall play on the hole of the Aſpe, and the weaned child ſhall put his hand on the cockatrice den. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy mountain: for the earth ſhall be full of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Lord,</hi> as the waters cover the Sea. Unto the which <hi>God, Father, Sonne,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Rev. 5.13.</note> be bleſſing, honour, and glory, and power, for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
            <q>
               <p>O houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> come ye, and let us walke in the light of the <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2.5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
